<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The saints legacies, or A collection of certaine promises out of the word of God Collected for the priuate use, but published for the comfort of Gods people. Whereunto is now added the saints support in times of trouble.</title>
            <title>Collection of certaine promises out of the word of God.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1629</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 179 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 125 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00502</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 10636</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S122118</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99857270</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99857270</idno>
            <idno type="VID">22966</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00502)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 22966)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1023:07)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The saints legacies, or A collection of certaine promises out of the word of God Collected for the priuate use, but published for the comfort of Gods people. Whereunto is now added the saints support in times of trouble.</title>
                  <title>Collection of certaine promises out of the word of God.</title>
                  <author>Fawkner, Antony, b. 1601 or 2, attributed name. aut</author>
                  <author>Farindon, Anthony, 1598-1658, attributed name. aut</author>
                  <author>A. F.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <editionStmt>
                  <edition>The 6. edition.</edition>
               </editionStmt>
               <extent>[32], 157, [3]; [2], 31, [23] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Leonrd Lichfield, for Richard Royston, in Ivy Lane,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Oxford :</pubPlace>
                  <date>An. Dom. 1640.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The compiler's initials, A.F., appeared in the 1931 ed.; possibly by Antony Fawkner or Anthony Farindon.--Cf. STC.</note>
                  <note>"The saints support in times of trouble" has separate dated title page.</note>
                  <note>Originally published in 1529 as: A collection of certaine promises out of the word of God.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Meditations --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:22966:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22966:1"/>
            <p>THE SAINTS LEGACIES, OR A COLLECTION OF CERTAINE PROMISES OVT OF THE WORD OF GOD.</p>
            <p>Collected for private uſe, but publiſhed for the comfort of Gods people.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Whereunto is now added the Saints Support in times of trouble.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>THE 6. EDITION.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by <hi>Leonard Lichfield,</hi> for <hi>Richard Royſton,</hi> in Ivy Lane. <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1640.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:22966:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:22966:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE and happy Society of all true Believers militant in
<list>
                  <item>ENGLAND,</item>
                  <item>SCOTLAND,</item>
                  <item>&amp; IRELAND.</item>
               </list>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">A Friend to you, and the <hi>Author,</hi> wiſheth fulneſſe of Grace, Peace, and heavenly comfort, certaine aſſurance ſealed evidence, and ſeaſonable entrance into, and poſſeſſion of the celeſtiall, promiſed, incorruptible, undefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led and never fading inheritance.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Eloved Believers, both you and I, are infinitely behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to our ever li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving Father, who hath made
<pb facs="tcp:22966:3"/>his will and given all us his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren great wealth, rich porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and large Legacies, now in preſent poſſesſion; graces, and comforts, in unſhaken expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and aſſured reverſion, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection and eternall glory. Wee are greatly beholding to <hi>Iehova,</hi> for his will directory, hortato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, correctory, but moſt of all for his will conſolatory, in which, he ſalves all our ſores; phyſicks all our ſickneſſes, me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>decines all our maladies, <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 103.4. Heales all our diſeaſes, and crownes us with loving kindneſſe and tender mercies. And ſurely wee are all of us
<pb facs="tcp:22966:3"/>much beholding to the holy Authour of this ſweet (though little) Book, who hath ſo piouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, painfully, and profitably pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruſed the holy will of our hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father, and wiſely ſought and found out and put into our hands, the ſpirituall portion, and Soule-Legacies, given and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queathed unto us by our beſt friend, many of which, moſt of ſcarce knew of, few ſought and ſued for them, and very few comfortable enjoyed and wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and diligently uſed to the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nors glory and their own good. Careleſſe children, come often<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times to be beholden unto their
<pb facs="tcp:22966:4"/>more carefull brethren and thri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving friends, who ſave all they have, ſue for all that is promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, and ſeek for all they heare of: ſo is it here, wee careleſſe, negligent, poore and ill thriven Chriſtians, muſt be beholding to this carefull, diligent, rich and well thriven Authour, who obeyes <hi>Pauls</hi> counſell, 1. <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.31. Covets earneſtly the beſt gifts and will not ſuffer the heavenly Father, to purſe and keep a pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny that is due, to with-hold grace or comfort (which hee hath promiſed) in whole, or degree, but he ſhall heare of his promiſe, and if he doe not pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſently
<pb facs="tcp:22966:4"/>fulfill according to cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, a petition is ſpeedily drawne, to be preferred in the Court of heaven, and an Advo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cate prepared Jeſus Chriſt the righteous. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 2.1. Suite (by prayer) begun, and in an eager purſuit continued, till the thing promiſed be performed.</p>
            <p>This little Book, and private practiſe of the Author (who hath ſued for all theſe Legacies, and in ſome good meaſure hath attained the ſame, and thereby is become ſpirituall rich) will ſufficiently prove what I have ſpoken. Wee are much behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den to this Author, for letting us
<pb facs="tcp:22966:5"/>ſee our Portions and Legacies in our Fathers will, and ſetting us a worke both by penne and practiſe to ſue for the ſame.</p>
            <p>The volume is little, but the vertue contained in the ſame is great. The book is extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, being altogether for applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and practiſe. The ſcope and drift of it is, to furniſh Believers with abundance of good; to free them from all ſins inward, outward, ſecret, and open; To fill them with all graces in life, power, and exerciſe; To bring them comfort in, and ſeaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble deliverance from all their troubles; To draw down upon
<pb facs="tcp:22966:5"/>their foules and bodies abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of blesſings of all ſorts and natures: to give them full aſſurance of certaine and ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable entrance into glory, and to give them faſt hold of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</p>
            <p>There are many, I know, that will little regard it: the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane perſon will not like it, for it is full of holineſſe: the car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall Proteſtant will not diſcern of it, nor reliſh it, for it is ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall: the diſſembling hypocrite will not well approve of it, for it will rob him of his <hi>Rimmon,</hi> ſlay his M<hi rend="sup">ris</hi>, his <hi>Dalilah,</hi> his <hi>Herodias,</hi> his darling ſin, it will
<pb facs="tcp:22966:6"/>tell him, if he applyes promiſes, he muſt keepe the conditions, obey precept, and put every ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quty, though never ſo pleaſura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble or profitable, farre away from his Tabernacles. But the honeſt hearted and ſincere Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever will approve of it, prize it, uſe it, and profit by it.</p>
            <p>And not to overcommend my commodity, as one deſirous to make it more vendible and ſaleable (for neither I, nor its Authour, God is witneſſe, ayme at any ſuch thing, but at the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall good of their ſoules unto whom it ſhall come) this little Book, like a well filled lttle A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pothecaries
<pb facs="tcp:22966:6"/>ſhop, containes within it heavenly receipts of all ſorts, wholeſome phyſick of every kind for expelling and cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring all ſorts of diſeaſes and ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes incident to Saints, and for the corroborating and ſtrengthning of new nature, and for keeping the ſpirituall man in good health, luſty and ſtrong able for Gods ſervice, <hi>Phil.</hi> 2.12. and for working out his owne ſalvation with feare and tremb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling. What here J ſpeake unto one Believer, I intend for all.</p>
            <p>Hath ſin that deadly poyſon infected thee? Loe here in this little Book an Antidote, a pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervative
<pb facs="tcp:22966:7"/>which will extract and expell this poyſon. Hath this ſerpent ſo fiery ſtung thee? <hi>Num.</hi> 21.8. Loe here the <hi>Brazen Serpent</hi> upon the pole. Hath it beggered and undone thee? <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.14, 15. Behold a way in this Book, how thou maiſt become rich. Doth it daily trouble thee; will it needs tirannize and do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mineere over thee? This little Book will learn thee to depoſe this tyrant, <hi>Rom.</hi> 6.14. and tell thee he ſhall not have domini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Lordſhip over thee Hath it ſtricken thee dead? Loe heres means of reviving and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>living thee, to an happy life of
<pb facs="tcp:22966:7"/>grace. Doth it threaten thy ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine? Loe here Phyſick for thy feares, <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.35. death hath loſt its ſting, ſin is deſtroyed, death ſhall fully and finally free thee from it. Art thou hunted like a poore Lambe by the helliſh de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouring Lyon, Sathan, and cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed before this infernall dog, like a ſilly Deere, in temptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? Loe here a thicket, a ſhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, a ſheepheard, under which thou maiſt repoſe and reſt thy ſelf in ſafety. Art thou overcome with his wilie ſtratagems? Loe here wiſdome. Art thou beaten downe with his power? Loe here ſtrength. Feareſt thou the
<pb facs="tcp:22966:8"/>fiery darts of this evill one? Loe here a little houſe full of targets, ſhields, and bucklers, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 6.16. (promiſes applyed by faith) which will repell and quench them. <hi>Iob</hi> 6.4. Doe Gods ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours ſet themſelves in array a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt thee? are Gods arrowes in thee? doth his ſlaming wrath burne in thy boſome, and is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to conſume thee? Loe ſtreams of mercy and grace from a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>freſhing fountaine, fluent in the pipes of the promiſes, by thy hand of faith turn the cock, and the coole water of Gods grace and mercy ſhall flow forth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on thy ſoule, and allay its burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb facs="tcp:22966:8"/>heat, and inflamations. Doth the wilie world endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to entangle and inveagle thee by its lures and ſnares? Loe here liberty, freedome, better things propounded, and promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which Believers doe for the preſent in ſome meaſure en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy, and ſhall have a moſt cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine and full poſſesſion of af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards. Wanteſt thou Grace, comfort, deliverance, blesſing, or any good thing? Behold, here thou maiſt have them, to the great joy of thine heart, and content of thy Spirit.</p>
            <p>Set faith a work to draw out what thou wanteſt, and thou
<pb facs="tcp:22966:9"/>ſhalt have it. Sucke theſe ſweet and heavenly breaſts of God by the mouth of thy faith; open theſe pipes and veines of the promiſes, which runne ſo full of mercy, grace, truth, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fort, joy and peace, for every Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liever, by faith; and thou ſhalt bee ſatiate with every good thing.</p>
            <p>Leſt I ſhould make too great a porch for this little houſe, and too great gates for this little Cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, I will conclude, with an ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation to all my beloved brethren and ſiſters which are Believers, to perfect their faith by application of the promiſes,
<pb facs="tcp:22966:9"/>both of theſe in this ſweet little Book, and of all others, contai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned in the Old and New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</p>
            <p>Suffer not Gods promiſes (as J may ſo ſay) to milke them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, doe you draw them, let not good reſt with God, which you may have by believing and begging, to your great comfort and enriching, but take Gods commodities off his hand, trade with that wealthy Merchant in the farre Countrey, the Lord Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus in heaven, for his rich com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modities of graces and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts, and glorious hopes, untill you be rich and wealthy; and
<pb facs="tcp:22966:10"/>for this purpoſe cauſe thoſe two good factours, <hi>Faith</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> founded upon and quickned and confirmed by the pretious promiſes, alway to trade for you in heaven, untill you come thither your ſelves. I would deſire all Believers to make this their pocket booke that it may ſollicite and woe them to prayer, make ſolid and firme their faith, increaſe their graces, comforts, and heavenly hopes, prepare them for endu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the ſtormes of trouble and tempeſts of temptations, and may encourage them in holy well-doing and Chriſtian per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeverance
<pb facs="tcp:22966:10"/>unto the end. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12. Now brethren, my hearts deſire is, that ye be not ſlothfull, but followers of them who through faith and patience in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herit the Promiſes.</p>
            <p>That you may be inheritours of them, it ſhall bee my daily prayer unto the Lord my God, to beſtow upon your hearts to uſe all good meanes, for the at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of the good, in theſe and other promiſes of God unto his people. That he would teach and enable you to meditate up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them diligently day and night, to believe them firmely; to apply them ſeverally, particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>larly,
<pb facs="tcp:22966:11"/>perſonally, to ſue for them earneſtly by prayer conſtant and fervent, to waite for their promiſed accompliſhment by patience, that ſo you may enjoy the good of them here and here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after, which God in mercy grant unto me, and alſo you. AMEN.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:22966:11"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>AN which at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning was created happy, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1.26. <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2.10. having now loſt God and his Image, is of all earthly creatures become moſt miſerable, no leſſe then a ſlave of the Devill, a child of wrath, &amp; an heire of eternall damnation. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.2, 3. This is not the eſtate of a few onely, but of all mankind out of Chriſt; for we are all by nature under the curſe. 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 4.4. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.19. <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.10. The beſt, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their converſion, were by nature children of wrath, even as others: <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.3. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.12. for every wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans
<pb facs="tcp:22966:12"/>child did fall equally in <hi>Adam:</hi> hence it comes to paſſe, that no man by nature is now in better eſteem with God then other. <hi>Cain</hi> and <hi>Abel</hi> as children of the firſt <hi>Adam</hi> onely were equally miſerable; the like may bee ſaid of us all, for both Iewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles are come under ſin. <hi>Rom.</hi> 3.9. And as the <hi>Pſalmiſt</hi> ſaith, We all are gone out of the way, we are altogether become filthy, there is none righteous, no not one. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 14.3. O that men and women had their eyes enlightened, and judgements convinced of that woeful plight in which naturally they are! Oh! were their hearts throughly loaden therewith, ſurely they would not long content themſelves therein. The truth is, moſt in the world are ſpiritually blind, and cannot diſcerne their owne miſery; and ſpiritually dead too, 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5.19. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2.1.5. and cannot be affected with it: The Holy
<pb facs="tcp:22966:12" rendition="simple:additions"/>Ghoſt ſaith thus of them, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4.18, 19. <hi>They walke in the vanity of their mind having their underſtanding dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, and are strangers from the life of God, through the ignorance which is in them, becauſe of the hardneſſe of their hearts: who being paſt feeling, have gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven themſelves unto wantonneſſe, to worke all uncleaneſse with greedineſſe.</hi> Such as theſe, are ſo farre from having any right to Gods promiſes, that for the preſent they are under the curſe, and conſequently in the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>nt of all the plagues &amp; threatnings in Gods Book. <hi>Deut.</hi> 27. <hi>ult. Deut.</hi> 28.56.63. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let not ſuch as yet challenge any comfort from the Promiſes, but let them after labour to the uttermoſt of their power, in uſing all good meanes to bee made capable and fit ſubjects for mercy revealed in the Promiſes. Is it not pitty ſo many ſweet Promiſes of life ſhould bee
<pb facs="tcp:22966:13"/>made, and yet thou dye and bee dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned notwithſtanding? Pray fervently to God that hee would touch thy heart with griefe for all thy ſins, and worke in thee a cleare apprehenſion of thine owne unworthineſſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2.37. <hi>Luke</hi> 15.19. and that he would be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtow faith on thee, that by it thou maiſt bee able to goe wholly out of thy ſelfe to God, through Ieſus Chriſt for ſalvation.</p>
            <p>Wee having departed from him who is the God of all grace and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation, are fallen into an eſtate of all baſeneſſe, deſolation, and miſery; and cannot bee recovered againe into the former eſtate of ſpirituall life and happineſſe, unleſſe wee be brought a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine to him who is the foundation of life and happineſſe, even the living God: and brought to him we can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be, but by Faith, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.6. which is nothing elſe but the going out of the
<pb facs="tcp:22966:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>ſoule to God through Chriſt, to fetch a new principle of ſpirituall life and grace, which once in <hi>Adam</hi> we loſt, and now need. The which worke of faith is not wrought but by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes; and being wrought in our hearts, gives us a moſt ſure right and intereſt <hi>unto all the promiſes of Grace. Rom.</hi> 10.8.17. <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.12.17. Thus we through faith and patience are ſaid to inherit the promiſes, therefore we are called the heires of the promiſe: the promiſes are as well ours, who truly believe, as heaven it ſelfe is. Now by theſe heavenly Promiſes, God our Father hath engaged himſelfe as a debtour to us his poore children for all things needfull to life and godlineſſe, 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.3. untill that bleſſed time comes when wee ſhall be put into full poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſſion of all things which wee have now only in promiſe: at that time <hi>Faith</hi> ſhall end in fruition, and <hi>Promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:22966:14"/>in performance. As the ſoule is the life of the body, and faith the life of the ſoule, ſo are Gods promiſes the life of faith. For from whence hath faith his efficacy, but becauſe it layes hold on the free promiſes? but from whence have the promiſes their ſtrength? even from the conſtant na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of <hi>Iehovah,</hi> 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 1.20. who al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes gives a being to his word. De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt thou faith? then take notice of Gods promiſes: wouldſt thou have thy faith like the light in the Lords Sanctuary never to goe out? then ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quaint thy ſelfe with Gods <hi>Promiſes,</hi> know them well, meditate on them, conferre about them: let them be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually in thy mind, memory, heart and tongue. Satan laboureth in no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more then to keepe us in unbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liefe, eſpecially of particular promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, for he knowes if we believe them, we ſhall in all things have the victory,
<pb facs="tcp:22966:14"/>come before God with boldneſſe, car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry peace in our owne boſomes to our graves, and doe, and ſuffer any thing for God. 1. <hi>Iohn</hi> 5. <hi>Eph.</hi> 2. <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. Oh the abundance of ſweet cordiall comfort which all humble beleevers draw by faith out of every promiſe! Now beloved, theſe pretious <hi>Promiſes</hi> (our breaſts of conſolation) whereupon our happineſſe ſo much depends, lye hid in the holy Scripture, as veines of gold in the earth. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66.11.12. Surely, thoſe that ſearch thoſe mynes to bring to light theſe trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, are worthy of great comme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Wherefore I doubt not but the good paines of this bleſſed and faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full ſervant of God will find good entertainment of all the children of the promiſes, that hope to entertaine them, who hath with great care and good evidence of ſpirituall underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding diſcovered and compiled the va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety
<pb facs="tcp:22966:15"/>and uſe of all the promiſes in matters temporall, ſpirituall, and eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall. So that here is a medicine for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very diſeaſe, and a ſalve for every ſore. Read them carefully and ponder them ſeriouſly, and apply them faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully. And I beſeech the good Lord, who is the Authour of them, that by his holy Spirit he would make them powerfull, and effectuall in us. <hi>Conſider what is ſaid, and the Lord give us underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding in all things.</hi> 2. Tim. 2.7.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="list_of_rules">
            <pb facs="tcp:22966:15" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>RVLES TO BE OBSERVED IN READING OF <hi>PROMISES.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hatſoever Promiſe is made in generall to all the faithfull, every one muſt particularly apply it to themſelves, as <hi>Gen. 3.14.</hi> the <hi>Meſſiah</hi> is promiſed to all, every one muſt apply him to them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <hi>2.</hi> Whatſoever promiſe is made to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny one of the faithfull (if there be not ſome particular reaſon which tyes it to his perſon, as was to <hi>Abraham</hi> for a ſonne, and his ſeed to inherit the land of Canaan) every child of God hath right to it: as you may ſee, <hi>Ioſhuah 1.5. I will
<pb facs="tcp:22966:16" rendition="simple:additions"/>not faile thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> This every one may apply to themſelves, as wee know the Holy Ghoſt applyes it, <hi>Heb. 13.5. For he hath ſaid, I will ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver leave thee, nor forſake thee.</hi> Which teacheth us to doe the like in all the reſt of the promiſes.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <hi>3.</hi> Vnder temporall promiſe to the Iewes, are ſet forth the excellent promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed graces, which God will give to his people after the comming of Christ, <hi>Ezek. 34.25, 26, 27.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">
               <hi>4.</hi> When wee read the conditions of the promiſes, they are not like to the du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Law, made to the perfect ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fillers of them; the promiſes are Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gelicall, made to thoſe which endeavour to keep them, and the maine conditions of them are ſaith.</p>
            <p n="5">
               <hi>5.</hi> In all the promiſes for increaſe of grace, or meanes of grace, or for any earthly things, we muſt know wee ſhall have them ſo farre performed to us, as
<pb facs="tcp:22966:16"/>the Lord ſeeth good for us.</p>
            <p n="6">
               <hi>6.</hi> In our weak endeavourings to keep the promiſes, we muſt believe the performance to us, in, by, and through Chriſt; <hi>In whom all the promiſes of God are yea, and Amen,</hi> that is, as <hi>I</hi> conceive, confirmed and made good to us in him, <hi>2. Cor. 1.20.</hi> when we can ſee nothing in our ſelves why they ſhould be performed to us, even then we are to claime them for Chriſts ſake; if thou be in Chriſt: for if thou bee not in him, no promiſe belongs to thee: but that threatnings and judgements are thy portion, and nothing elſe can wee claime as our due. Sorrow, weeping, and bowling is that which God requireth of us, and not laying hand upon the comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table promiſes, till wee hunger after Chriſt; which God grant wee may doe more and more, till we come to be ſatisfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with his image in the life to come. <hi>Pſal. 17.15.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:17"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22966:17"/>
                  <head>THE FIRST LEGACY.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Theſe promiſes I have obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved for ſpirituall things.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>FIRST ABOVT SINNE.</hi> If we find nothing in our ſelves that may move God.</head>
                     <p>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hen we find nothing in our ſelves that might move the Lord to have mercy, then apply theſe promiſes, Iſai. 43.25. <hi>I, even I am be, that blotteth out
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:22966:18"/>thy tranſgresſion for mine own ſake, &amp; will not remember thy ſinnes,</hi> Iſai 44.22. <hi>I have blotted out as a thicke cloud thy tranſgresſions, and as a cloud thy ſinnes: returne unto me, for I have re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ier. 31.34. <hi>I will forgive their ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity, and remember their ſinne no more.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ezek. 36.25. <hi>I will ſprinkle cleane water upon you, and yee ſhall bee cleane from all your filthineſs.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 57.18. <hi>I have ſeene his wayes, and will heale him, I will lead him alſo, and restore comforts unto him, and to his mourners.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe promiſes are free, made by the Lord, not for any thing that is in man, as you may ſee, in <hi>Iſaiah</hi> 43. from the 22. verſe, to the 25. for the Lord ſaith, They had not called upon him, but wearied the Lord, brought him no offering, yea wearied him
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22966:18"/>with their ſinnes; and yet in the 25. verſe hee ſaith, for his owne ſake hee would forgive their ſinnes.</p>
                     <p>Theſe promiſes wee ſhall have al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes need of, as at our converſion, ſo afterwards many times wee ſhall in our owne feeling finde nothing in our ſelves to perſwade us of the pardon of our ſinnes, then wee muſt flye to theſe free promiſes. When thou ſeeſt nothing in thy ſelfe why the Lord ſhould pardon thy ſinnes, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore doubt'ſt of the pardon of them, apply, <hi>I am he that puts away thy ſinnes for mine owne ſake.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thy ſinnes riſe up as a cloud, that thou canſt ſee nothing but them, apply, <hi>I have put away thy ſinnes as a cloud.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou feareſt the multitude of thy ſinnes, apply, <hi>You ſhall be cleane from all your ſinnes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:22966:19"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE II. LEGACY.</hi> If we feare, God will remember our ſinnes to puniſh them.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When wee fear, God will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member our ſinnes before committed, to puniſh us for them, apply Ier. 31.34.</hi> I will remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber his ſinne no more <hi>Ezek. 18.22.</hi> His tranſgresſions which hee hath commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ſhall not be mentioned to him, but in the righteouſneſſe which hee hath done, ſhall he live.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ezek. 33.16.</hi> None of his ſinnes that he hath committed ſhall be mentio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:22966:19"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE III. LEGACY.</hi> If often ſinning cauſe thee doubt of pardon.</head>
                     <p>WHen thine often ſinning cauſeth thee to feare that God will not pardon thee, apply, Iob. 33.27.28.29. <hi>He looketh upon men, and if any ſay I have ſinned, and perverted that which was right, and it profiteth me not: hee will deliver his ſoule from going into the pit, and his life ſhall ſee the light.</hi> Loe all theſe things worketh God, oftentimes with man. Wherefore believe not Satan that perſwades the contrary, nor let thy corruptions make thee bold to preſume of pardon; for though God promiſe pardon, yet it is to the
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:22966:20" rendition="simple:additions"/>penitent, not to the preſumptuous, as verſ. 27.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE IV. LEGACY.</hi> If thou deſpaire.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou art at the pits brinke of deſpaire, and art dryed up with ſorrow, then goe to ſome faithfull Preacher that is able to preach Chriſt unto thee, and apply theſe promiſes: Iob. 33.24, 25, 26. <hi>Then he is gracious unto him, and ſaith, deliver him from going downe to the pit, I have found a ranſome. His fleſh ſhall bee freſher then a childs, hee ſhall returne to the dayes of his youth. He ſhall pray unto God, and he ſhall be favourable unto him, and he ſhall ſee his face with joy: for he will render unto
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:22966:20"/>man his righteouſneſſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 57.19. <hi>I create the fruit of the lips, peace, peace, to him that is farre off, and to him that is neare, ſaith the Lord, and I will heale him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou commeſt to the utter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt extremity for ſinne, apply, <hi>I will have mercy on him, and deliver him, that he goe not downe to the pit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou feareſt that God or his Miniſters will not ſpeake peace unto thee, apply, I <hi>have received a reconci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liation. I create the fruit of the lips to be peace, to them that are farre off, and to them that are neare.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thy ſorrowes have withered thee up, apply, <hi>He ſhall returne as in the dayes of his youth, and his fieſh ſhall be as the fleſh of a child.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If in this eſtate thou feareſt, God will not heare prayers for thee, apply, <hi>He ſhall pray to God, and he will be fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vourable to him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:22966:21"/>
                     <p>When thou feareſt thou ſhalt not be able to looke upon the Lord with joy, apply, <hi>Hee ſhall ſee his face with joy.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou ſeeſt not any thing in thy ſelfe, that ſhould cauſe thee not to believe this, apply, <hi>He will render to man his righteouſneſse;</hi> which is (I thinke) Chriſts righteouſneſſe, for whoſe ſake he will doe it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE V. LEGACY.</hi> If thou findeſt ſinne an heavy bur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den, and Satan purſuing.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou feeleſt ſin an hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy burden, and Satan purſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing thee with many feares, by reaſon of the ſame, flye to Chriſt, and apply, Matth. 11.28, 29. <hi>Come
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:22966:21"/>unto me all yee that labour and are hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy laden, and I will give you reſt.</hi> Mat. 1.21. <hi>He ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rom. 16.20. <hi>And the God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 32.2. <hi>And a man ſhall bee as a hiding place from the wind, and a co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert from the tempeſt, as rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters in a dry place, as the ſhadow of a great rocke in a weary land.</hi> Thus doth Chriſt to the ſoule that flyes to him.</p>
                     <p>If Satan purſue thee, apply, <hi>He is an hiding place.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If ſtormes of temptations and affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions doe ariſe, apply, <hi>He is a refuge againſt the tempeſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thy ſoule bee ready to faint through weakeneſſe, apply, <hi>He is a ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of water in a dry place,</hi> to revive thy ſpirits, and as the ſhadow of a great rocke, under which thou maiſt
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22966:22"/>ſafely repoſe thy ſelfe. When thou findeſt thy ſinnes very heavy, apply, <hi>I wil eaſe you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou haſt no reſt in thy foule becauſe of ſinne, apply, <hi>You ſhall find rest to your ſoules.</hi> Hee ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes, both from the puniſhment and the power.</p>
                     <p>If thou feareſt length of time in temptations, apply, <hi>The God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet ſhort<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE VI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou turne from ſinne, and yet doubt of pardon.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou turneſt from ſin, and doubteſt of the pardon of it, apply, Iſai. 1.18.</hi>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:22966:22"/>Though your ſins be as ſckarlet, they ſhall be as white as ſnow, though they be red like crimſon, they ſhall bee as wooll.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 55.7.</hi> Let the wicked forſake his way, and the unrighteous man his thoughts, and let him returne unto the Lord, and he will have mercy on him, and to our God, for he will abundantly pardon.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Micah. 7.18, 19.</hi> Who is a God like unto thee, that pardoneth iniquity, and paſseth by the tranſgreſsion of the rem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of his beritage? hee retaineth not his anger for ever, becauſe he delighteth in mercy. He will turne againe, he will have compaſsion upon us, he will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due our iniquities, and thou wilt caſt all their ſinnes into the depths of the ſea. <hi>Prov. 21.13.</hi> He that confeſseth and forſaketh his ſinnes, ſhall find mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy. <hi>1. Ioh. 1.9.</hi> If we confeſſe our ſins, he is faithfull and juſt to forgive us our
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:22966:23"/>ſinnes, and to cleanſe us from all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou ſeeſt thy ſoule of a ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full colour, apply,</hi> Though they be red like crimſon, they ſhall be as white as wool.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If thou feareſt God will hardly be intreated, apply,</hi> He will have mercy, for he is ready to forgive.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If we feare that our ſinnes have ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken ſuch ſtrong hold upon us, as wee ſhall never get from them, apply,</hi> He will cleanſe us from all our unrighteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Seeing God promiſeth to be the cleanſer, feare not the hardneſſe of the worke.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:22966:23"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE VII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wouldſt have thy mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fold rebellions ſubdued.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou feeleſt many rebellions in thine heart and life, and wouldſt have them not only pardoned, but ſubdued, apply, Hoſ. 14.5. <hi>I will heale their backe-ſliding.</hi> Which promiſe (as I thinke) containes thus much, that God will not only pardon, but heale us, and inſtead of rebellious hearts and lives, will give us obedient hearts and lives; for as healing follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the curing of ſickneſſe: ſo obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence doth the curing of rebellion. Micah. 7.19. <hi>He will ſubdue our iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:22966:24"/>
                     <p>When thou feeleſt ſin very ſtrong, flye to this promiſe, and apply the ſtrength of him that promiſeth, againſt then ſtrength of ſinne: it is the Lord that hath promiſed to ſubdue it; what though Sinne and Satan joyne their force together, yet the Lord is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then all their force, wee need not doubt.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE VIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thy heart bee hard and full of corruption.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou feeleſt thine heart hard, and full of corruption, apply, Ezek. 36.26. <hi>A new heart alſo will I give you, and a new ſpirit will I put within you, and I will take away the ſtony heart
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:22966:24"/> out of your fleſh, and I will give you an heart of fleſh.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Deut. 30.6. <hi>And the Lord thy God will circumciſe thine heart, and the heart of thy ſeed, to love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule, that thou maist live.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou feeleſt thine heart worldly carnall, apply, <hi>I will circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe thy heart. A new heart will I give thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When nothing will breake thine heart, apply the power of <hi>Iehovah,</hi> that hath promiſed to cure thee, in ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king away thy ſtony heart.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:22966:25"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE IX. LEGACY.</hi> If unbridled nature break out into pasſion.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou canſt not bri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle nature, but it breakes forth into violent paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, to contention, apply, Iſai. 11.6. <hi>The Wolfe alſo ſhall dwell with the Lambe, and the Leopard ſhall lye downe with the Kid, and the Calfe, and the young Lyon, &amp; the fatling together, &amp; a little child ſhall lead them.</hi> Such ſhall bee the power of the Goſpell, that thoſe which are by nature like Wolves and devouring beaſts, ſhall dwell very peaceably: and if wee find our nature ſuch, we muſt apply, <hi>the Wolfe ſhall dwell with the Lambe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:22966:25"/>
                     <p>Micah. 7.19. <hi>He will ſubdue our ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities, and will caſt all our ſinnes into the depth of the ſea:</hi> that which is caſt into the Sea, as it appeareth not in ſight, ſo wee cannot get it againe, though wee would: ſo will God doe by your ſinnes, caſt them out of his ſight, ſo as wee ſhall not returne to them any more: preſſe him with his promiſe, and you ſhall find more then you thinke.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE X. LEGACY.</hi> If thou be in bondage to ſome ſin.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou feeleſt thy ſelfe in bondage to ſome ſinne, apply, Iohn 8.32. <hi>You ſhall know the Truth, and the truth ſhall make you free.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Rom. 6.14. <hi>Sinne ſhall not have
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:22966:26"/>dominion you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou feeleſt thy bondage that thou canſt not doe good, or keep thy ſelfe from evill; apply. <hi>The truth ſhall make you free.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thy ſinnes often prevaile againſt thee, apply, <hi>Sinne ſhall not have domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion over you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pſal. 130.8. <hi>He ſhall redeeme</hi> Iſrael <hi>from all his iniquities.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou feareſt the breaking out of strong ſinnes.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou feeleſt ſome ſinne ſo ſtrong in thee, that thou feareſt it will breake out to Gods diſhonour, and the blemiſhing of Religion, apply, 1.
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22966:26"/>Theſſ. 5.23.24. <hi>That your whole ſpirit, ſoule and body may be preſerved blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse unto the comming of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. Faithfull is he that calleth you, who alſo will doe it.</hi> That God which hath called thee, will keep thee blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe unto the comming of Chriſt: therefore uſe the meanes, and reſt up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lords faithfulneſſe which ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver faileth them which truſt in him.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. Theſ. 3.3. <hi>But the Lord is faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, who ſhall ſtabliſh you and keepe you from evill.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. Ioh. 1.9. <hi>If we confeſse our ſinnes, he is faithfull and just to forgive us our ſinnes, and to cleanſe us from all unrigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſse.</hi> By cleanſing (as I thinke) is meant not onely from the guilt of ſinne, but the the power of it, that the filthineſſe of it ſhall not appeare in our lives and converſations. When ſinne purſues thee hard to make thee fall, doe thou purſue the Lord with
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:22966:27"/>prayers, for performance of this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, and doubt not of the iſſue.</p>
                     <p>Micah 7.19. <hi>Hee will ſubdue our iniquities.</hi> And to theſe adde the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of Chriſt, Iohn 17.15. <hi>I pray not that thou ſhouldſt take them out of the world, but that thou ſhouldſt keepe them from the evill.</hi> Now what grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter evill than ſinne? therefore though thy prayers bee but weake againſt it, yet hee hath prayed that was al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way heard, therefore fight and be ſure of victory.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XII LEGACY.</hi> When thou art ſtayed from ſinne by admonition.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou art ſtayed from ſinne by admonition, appy, Ezek. 3.21. <hi>If thou warne the
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:22966:27"/>righteous man, that the righteous ſinne not, and he doth not ſin, he ſhall ſurely live becauſe he is warned.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When any admoniſh thee, obey, and it ſhall bee life to thy ſoule, therefore receive the admonition, and apply, <hi>He ſhall live, becauſe he is admoniſhed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou feareſt God will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroy thee for ſin.</head>
                     <p>IF thou feareſt, God will deſtroy thee for thy ſinnes, apply, Ezek. 18.30. <hi>Turne your ſelves from all your tranſgreſsions, ſo iniquity ſhall not be your ruine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Matth. 1.21. <hi>He ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou feareſt the greatneſſe or
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:22966:28"/>multitude of thy ſinnes will bee thy deſtruction, apply, <hi>Iniquity ſhall not be your ruine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou ſeeſt no meanes of ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, apply, <hi>He</hi> (that is, Chriſt) <hi>ſhall ſave his people from their ſinnes.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XIV LEGACY.</hi> If thou be tempted to uncleannes.</head>
                     <p>IF thou be tempted to uncleanneſſe, apply, Prov. 2.16. <hi>Hee ſhall deliver thee from the strange woman.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p n="1">1. Theſ. 5.24. <hi>Thy body ſhall bee kept blameleſse untill the comming of Chriſt.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:22966:28"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XV. LEGACY.</hi> If thou canst not find out thy ſin, for which God corrects thee.</head>
                     <p>IF thou canſt not find out thy ſinne, for which God correcteth thee, apply, Iob. 39.9. <hi>If they bee tyed with the cords of affliction, then will I ſhew them their worke, and their ſins.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>A wiſe Father will not correct his child, but hee will ſhew him where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, how elſe ſhould hee amend his fault? much more will the Lord. But we enjoy not many promiſes, becauſe we ſue not for them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thus farre about Sin, the next about Grace.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="24" facs="tcp:22966:29"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XVI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou doubt of ſalvation.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>In doubt of ſalvation, apply,</hi> God ſo loved the world, that he gave his on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly begotten Sonne, that whoſoever believeth in him, ſhould not periſh, but have everlaſting life, <hi>Iohn 3.16.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iohn 5.24.</hi> Hee that heareth my word, and believeth on him that ſent me, hath everlasting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation, but is paſſed from death unto life.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iohn 8.51.</hi> If any many keepe my ſaying, he ſhall never ſee death.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iohn 11.25.</hi> Hee that believeth in me, though hee were dead, yet ſhall hee live. And whoſoever believeth in mee ſhall never ſee death.</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:22966:29"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If thou doubt that thou ſhalt periſh, and not be ſaved, apply,</hi> Hee that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieves in <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhall not periſh, but ſhall have everlaſting life, and ſhall not come into condemnation. <hi>Labour to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve theſe Promiſes, for that is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of thee, for the obtaining of what is promiſed.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XVII. LEGACY.</hi> If thine heart bee as a wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe, barren of good.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou findeſt thine heart as a wilderneſſe barren of good, apply, Eſai. 35.1, 2. <hi>The wilderneſse and the ſolitary place ſhall bee glad for them: and the deſart ſhall rejoyce, and bloſſome as the Roſe, It ſhall bloſſome abundantly, and rejoyce
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:22966:30"/>even with joy and ſinging.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This promiſe is made to the Church, and every member of it may apply it to themſelves: therefore when thou feeleſt thine heart as a deſart wilderneſſe, and waſt ground, void of good, full of bryers and thornes of ſinne, then know, thou ſhalt not only bring forth ſweet ſmelling graces. like Roſes, but alſo all abundance of them.</p>
                     <p>Pro. 11.28. <hi>The righteous ſhal flou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh as a branch.</hi> Prov. 13.4. <hi>The ſoule of the diligent ſhall be made fat.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 14.5.6. <hi>I will be as the dew to</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>he ſhall grow as the Lilly, and cast forth his roots like</hi> Lebanon. <hi>His bran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches ſhall ſpread, &amp; his beauty ſhall be as the Olive tree &amp; his ſmell as</hi> Lebanon.</p>
                     <p>When wee want meanes to make us fruitfull, apply, <hi>The Lord will be a dew to Iſrael.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When wee deſire to flouriſh and grow vp in grace, apply, <hi>He ſhall grow
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22966:30"/>as the Lilly, his branches ſhall ſpread.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thou wouldeſt ſhine forth in the beauty of holynes, apply, <hi>His beauty ſhall be as the Olive-tree, and as the Lillies,</hi> whoſe glory is greater then <hi>Solomons</hi> in all his Royalty.</p>
                     <p>If thou wouldeſt have thy graces ſend forth a ſweet, ſmell, apply, <hi>His ſmell ſhall be as Lebanon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thou feareſt the continuance of this eſtate, apply, <hi>He ſhal fasten his roots, as ahe trees of Lebanon.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>It matters not how great our barren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe be, when God will be a dew to us: it will quickly make us fruitfull, we ſhall bring forth fruits glorious to the ſight as the Lilly, and as the Olive tree, and the ſent of our graces ſhall be a ſweet ſmelling ſavor, as the trees of Lebanon. Therefore though thou feeleſt thy heart yet barre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; thou haſt uſed means long, &amp; yet art not fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, ſtill uſe the meanes, and beleeve,
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:22966:31"/>for therein did <hi>Abraham</hi> glorifie God that hee beleeved above hope, that <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rah</hi> ſhould have a Son, whoſe wombe was barren, and by yeeres paſt child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing: ſo though thine heart remaine barren in thine own feeling, after long uſe of meanes, yet ſtill follow ſeeking in the meanes, and believe, for we have as ſure promiſes, and as faithfull a per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former, as <hi>Abraham</hi> had, Ieſus Chriſt, yeſterday, and to day, and the ſame for ever.</p>
                     <p>Iohn 7.38. <hi>He that believeth on me, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of water of life.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:22966:31"/>
                     <head>THE XVIII. LEGACY. <hi>If thou wanteſt holineſſe.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>WHen thou art troubled for want of holineſſe, apply, Exod. 19.6. <hi>You ſhall be an haly nation.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Deut. 28.9. <hi>And the Lord ſhall eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh thee an holy people unto himſelfe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lord will make thee holy; therefore Sinne, nor Satan, nor wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed men cannot hinder thy holineſſe: for he that makes thee holy, is ſtron<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger then all, and doth what he will.</p>
                     <p n="1">1. Theſſ. 5.23.24. <hi>The God of peace ſhall ſanctify you throughout, in ſpirit, ſoule, and body. Faithfull is he which calleth you, which will alſo doe it.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="30" facs="tcp:22966:32"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XIX. LEGACY.</hi> When thou canſt not offer up any ſacrifice.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou canſt not offer up any ſacrifice to God of prayer or prayſe, or thy ſelfe in ſacrifice, apply, Exod. 19.6. <hi>Yee ſhall bee unto mee a Kingdome of Priests.</hi> God promiſeth that wee ſhall be Prieſts, that is, ſuch as ſhall offer up ſacrifice unto him, for that was the Prieſts office. Therefore when thou findeſt thy ſelfe unable to pray, or praiſe the Lord, or to offer up thy ſelfe to God, ſoule and body, ſtrive in faith grounded on the promiſes, that he which commanded, hath alſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to make us able to doe it, for he
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22966:32"/>hath ſaid, <hi>We ſhall be Priests,</hi> Malac. 1.11. <hi>In every place incenſe ſhall bee off e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to my name, and a pure offering,</hi> which is ſpoken of the believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, therefore thou being one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſhalt be able to offer up pure offerings.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XX. LEGACY.</hi> When thou feeleſt but litle grace.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou feeleſt litle grace, knowledge, faith, love, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance, all very litle, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Iob. 8.7. <hi>Though thy beginning be ſmall, yet thy later end ſhall greatly in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Matth. 13.12. <hi>Whoſoever hath, to him ſhall bee given; and hee ſhall have abundance.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore let not thy ſmall begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nings
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:22966:33"/>diſcourage thee; but if thou canſt prove thou haſt ſome grace, then joyne faith and diligence together, and they will quickly make thee rich.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXI. LEGACY.</hi> When all thy graces are weake.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou findeſt all thy graces very weake, and no ſtrength to performe any ſpirituall duty, either prayer, or faſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, or any other duty, then apply, Pſal. 29.11. <hi>The Lord will give ſtrength unto his people.</hi> Iſai. 40.29.31. <hi>He giveth power to the faint, and to them which have no might hee increa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth ſtrength. They that wait upon the Lord, ſhall renew their ſtrength, they ſhall mount up with wings as Eagles
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:22966:33"/>they ſhall runne and not be weary, they ſhall walke and not faint.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou feeleſt by ſelfe faint, ſtay thy ſelfe with this promiſe, <hi>Hee gives ſtrength to him that fainteth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou feeleſt no power, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>to him that hath no ſtrength, he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſeth power.</hi> If thou haſt loſt thy power, then ſtay thy ſelfe with this, <hi>they ſhall renew their ſtrength.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thou art ready to give over through wearineſſe, then gather ſtrength from this, <hi>They ſhall run, and not bee weary, and walke, and not bee faint.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And if thou findeſt not theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes performed unto thee, either thou endeavoureſt not to keepe the conditions, or elſe thou art negligent in ſearching out the promiſes, or cold in ſuing for them: the Lord will bee ſought to for the performance.</p>
                     <p>Iſai. 41.10. <hi>I am thy God, I will
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:22966:34"/>ſtrengthen thee, yea I will helpe thee, yea I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſse.</hi> Iſa. 26.4. <hi>Truſt thou in the Lord for ever, for in the Lord</hi> Iehovah <hi>is everlasting ſtrength.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>To know there is ſtrength in the Lord is no comfort, unleſſe we know it ſhall be for us. Therefore ſince it is given for a comfort, it muſt include this promiſe, <hi>Thus the Lords strength for evermore ſhall bee imployed for our good.</hi> Therefore when we want for either ſoule or body, we muſt fixe our confidence in him, who will not faile us, if we ſeek unto him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:22966:34"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXII. LEGACY.</hi> When thy heart is dryed for want of Grace.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou feeleſt thy heart dryed up for want of grace that thou canſt not ſend forth any water of grace in thy thoughts, words, and works, apply, Iſa. 44.3.</hi> I will powre water upon him that is thirſty, and floods upon the drye ground.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 58.11.</hi> The Lord ſhall ſatisfy thy ſoule in drought, and make fat thy bones, and thou halt bee like a watred garden, and like a ſpring of waters, whoſe waters faile not.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ier. 17.8.</hi> He ſhall be as a tree planted by the waters, that ſpreadeth out her
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:22966:35"/>roots by the river, and ſhall not ſee when heat commeth: but her leafe ſhall bee green, and ſhall not bee carefull in the yeare of drought, neither ſhall ceaſe from yeilding fruit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ier. 31.12.</hi> Their ſoule ſhall beee as a watred garden.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iam. 4.6.</hi> God giveth grace unto the humble.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſa. 35.6, 7.</hi> In the wilderneſſe ſhall waters break out, and ſtreames in the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſert. And the parched ground ſhall be. come a poole and the thirſty land ſprings of waters. <hi>That is, the moſt barren heart ſhall abound with grace, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that promiſe. Ioh. 7.38.</hi> Out of their bellies ſhall flow rivers of the waters of Life.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſa. 41.17, 18.</hi> When the poore and needy ſeeke water, and there is none, and their tongues faile for thirst, <hi>I</hi> the Lord will heare them, <hi>I</hi> the God of Iſrael will not forſake them: I will open rivers in
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:22966:35"/>high places: and fountaines in the midſt of the valleyes: I will make the wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse a poole of water, and the drye land ſprings of water. I will plant in the wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſse the Cedar, the Shittah-tree, and the Mirtle, and the O live tree: I will ſet in the deſart the Firre-tree, and the Pine, and the Box tree together. <hi>So now though thou feeleſt thy heart barren, know that God will bee thy Gardiner to thy barren heart, to make pooles, and plant pleaſant grapes of graces; therefore ſeeing he taketh upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe the worke, feare not the badneſſe of the ground, for hee will make it good as a fruitfull garden.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="38" facs="tcp:22966:36"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wanteſt the ſpirit.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou feeleſt thou wanteſt the ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God, apply, Ezek. 36.27.</hi> I will put my ſpirit within you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Luke 11.13.</hi> If yee then being evill, know how to give good gifts unto your children: how much more ſhall your heavenly Father give the holy Spirit to them that aske him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ioel 2.28.29.</hi> I will powre out my Spirit upon all fleſh, and your ſonnes and your daughters ſhall propheſie, your old men ſhall dreame dreames, and your young men ſhall ſee viſions, And alſo up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the ſervants, &amp; upon th ehandmaids in thoſe dayes will <hi>I</hi> powre out my ſpirit.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ioh. 14.16.17.</hi> And <hi>I</hi> will pray the
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:22966:36"/>Father, and hee ſhall give you another Comforter, that he may abide with you for ever: even the Spirit of truth, hee dwelleth in you, and ſhall be in you, I will not leave you comfortleſse, I will come to you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou canſt not pray thy ſelfe, ſtay thy ſelfe on theſe prayers, that Chriſt hath prayed, to the Father to give the Spirit, and he was heard in all hee prayed for, therefore thou maiſt laime it, though thy prayers bee but weake.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXIV. LEGACY.</hi> If looking on Gods love, thou canſt not love God againe.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou lookeſt upon the great love of God unto thee, and canſt not finde
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:22966:37"/>thine heart inlarged in loving God again, apply this promiſe, Deut. 30.9. I <hi>will circumciſe thine heart, that thou maiſt love the Lord thy God with all thine heart, and with all thy ſoule.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXV. LEGACY.</hi> If thou canſt not bring thine heart to delight in the Lord.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou canſt not bring thine heart to delight in the Lord, apply, Iſai. 41.16.</hi> Thou ſhalt rejoyce in the Lord, and glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry in the holy one of <hi>Iſrael.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 89.16.</hi> In thy name ſhall they rejoyce all the day: and in thy righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe ſhall they be exalted.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iob. 22.26.</hi> For then ſhalt thou have thy delight in the Almighty.
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:22966:37"/>
                        <hi>Pſal. 33.21.</hi> For our heart ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in him, becauſe we have trusted in his holy name.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou ſeeſt cauſe of rejoycing in the Lord, and yet canſt not move thine affections, apply,</hi> They ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyce in him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If through many troubles and temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, thou findeſt thy joyes often interrupted, apply,</hi> they ſhall rejoyce continually in thy name.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXVI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou feeleſt not Gods feare in thine heart.</head>
                     <p>WHen wee feele not the feare of God, in our hearts, apply, Ier. 33.40. <hi>I will put my feare in their hearts.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:22966:38"/>
                     <p>If we would have a reverent feare of God, when we performe any holy duty, or at other times, as thou feeleſt thy need, ſo urge the Lord with this his promiſe, for he delights to be ſued to, upon his promiſe, by his ſervants, Ezek. 36.37. <hi>I will yet for this bee in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of by the houſe of</hi> Iſrael <hi>to doe it for them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXVII. LEGACY.</hi> If thine heart will not praiſe the Lord.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou canſt not bring thine heart to praiſe the Lord, apply Iſa. 43.21. <hi>This people have I formed for my ſelfe, they ſhall ſhew forth my praiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ioel 2.26. <hi>Yee ſhall eat in plenty, and
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:22966:38"/>be ſatisfied, and praiſe the name of the Lord your God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pſal. 22.29. <hi>They ſhall praiſe the Lord that ſeeke him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou ſeeſt what great things God hath done for thee, and findeſt not thy ſelf able to ſet forth his praiſe, apply, <hi>They ſhall ſet forth my praiſe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou findeſt thy ingratefull heart not affected with the mercies thou enjoyeſt, ſo as they ſtirre thee not up to praiſe the Lord, apply, <hi>Hee ſhall eat and be ſatisfied, and praiſe the name of the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXVIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wantest wiſdome.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou ſeeſt thy want of wiſdome makes thee not walke like a Chriſtian, ſo
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:22966:39"/>unblameably as thou ought, apply, Iam. 1.5. <hi>If any of you lacke wiſdome, let him aske of God that giveth to all men liberally, and upbraideth not, and it ſhall be given him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou findeſt thou want'ſt wiſdome to improve thine afflictions to the beſt advantage, or for the orde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of thy actions, occafions and courſe of life, to Gods glory and the good of others, and thy ſelfe, then faile not to aske wiſdome, and doubt not of the obtaining of it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXIX. LEGACY.</hi> If thou canſt not underſtand Gods voyce.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou canſt not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand the voyce of
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:22966:39"/>God in his word, or works, not know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing what to learne by them, apply, Iſa. 35.5. <hi>The eares of the deafe ſhall bee unſtopped.</hi> That is, thoſe that were deafe, not underſtanding any thing, ſhall be made to heare, that is, to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</p>
                     <p>Ioh. 10.16. <hi>Other ſheep I have, which are not of this fold, them alſo</hi> I <hi>muſt bring, and they ſhall heare my voyce.</hi> Which is a promiſe to the Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, that they ſhall underſtand the voyce of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXX. LEGACY.</hi> If thou cauſt not ſee into the mysteries of the Goſpell.</head>
                     <p>IF thou canſt not ſee into the divine my ſteries of the Goſpel, apply, Iſa.
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:22966:40"/>35.5. <hi>The eyes of the blind ſhall be ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned.</hi> Iſa. 42.7. <hi>Hee ſhall open thee eyes of the blind.</hi> Luk. 4.18. <hi>Hee hath ſent me to recover ſight to the blind.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Theſe places are what Chriſt will doe to his people, therefore wee need not feare our diſeaſe, ſeeing Chriſt is our Phyſitian. If every creature that, for which it was ordained, then hee will ſurely doe that which hee was ſent to doe of the Father, to give ſight to the blind.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXXI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou ſeeſt a good way and haſt no power to walke in it.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou ſeeſt a good way, and haſt no power to walke in it, or art to performe any
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:22966:40"/>duty, ordinary or extraordinary, and feeleſt no ſtrength to walke in that way, apply, Ezek. 36.72. <hi>And</hi> I <hi>will put my Spirit within you, and cauſe you to walke in my statutes, and ye ſhall keep my judgements, and doe them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou lookeſt at the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of the duty which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, looke alſo at the largeneſſe of his promiſes for the keeping of them, and then thou wilt not be diſcouraged at it. What matters it what hee com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands, ſeeing we have his promiſe?</p>
                     <p>If thou feareſt the ſtrictneſſe of thy wayes that thou ſhalt not bee able to walke in them, though thou ſtep into them ſometimes, ſtrengthen thy faith in this promiſe, I will give thee my Spirit to cauſe thee to walke in my wayes. Can Sinne or Satan then reſiſt Nay ſurely the Spirit is ſtronger, and greater is hee that is in us, then thoſe that are againſt us. And when wee ſee
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:22966:41"/>great duties which God commands, and feare wee ſhall want ſtrength to doe them, apply, Hee hath ſaid, <hi>You ſhall keep my judgements and doe them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 40.31. <hi>They ſhall runne, and not be weary, they ſhall walke and not bee faint.</hi> That is, Thoſe which of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves could not ſtep one ſtep, ſhall be able to runne ſwiftly in the wayes of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="32" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXXII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wanteſt memory.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>VVHen thou wanteſt me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory to remember the Word of God, apply, Ioh. 14.26.</hi> But the Comforter which is the holy Ghoſt, whom the Father will
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:22966:41"/>ſend in my name, hee ſhall teach you all things, and bring all things to your re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance, whatſoever I have ſaid un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to you.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="33" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXXIII. LEGACY.</hi> When thou ſeest thine ignorance.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>VVHen thou ſeeſt thine ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance, and feareſt thou ſhalt not bee able to glorify God as thou mighteſt, if thou had'ſt more knowledge, ſtirre up thy ſelfe to deſire and apply, Ier. 31.33.34.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, I will put my Law in their inward parts, and write it in their hearts, and they ſhall all know me, ſaith the Lord, from the greateſt to the least. <hi>Hoſea 2.20.</hi> Thou ſhalt know the Lord. <hi>Prov. 1.23.</hi> I will
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:22966:42"/>powre out my Spirit unto you, I will make knowne my words unto you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 25.9.12.14.</hi> The meek will hee guide in Iudgement: and the meek will he teach his way. What man is hee that ſeareth the Lord? him ſhall he teach in the way that he ſhall chuſe. The ſecret of the Lord is with them that feare him: and he will ſhew them his covenant.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prov. 2.4.9.11, 12, 13.</hi> If thou ſeek<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt her as ſilver, and ſearchest for her as for treaſures: Then ſhalt thou underſtand righteouſneſse, and judgement, and equi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, yea every good path. Diſcretion ſhall preſerve thee, understanding ſhall keep thee, to deliver thee from the way of the evill man, from the man that ſpeaketh froward things: who leave the paths of uprightneſse, to walke in the wayes of darkneſſe. <hi>Iſai. 11.9.</hi> The earth ſhall be full of the knowledge of the Lord. <hi>Prov. 8.17.</hi> Thoſe that ſeek me early ſhall find me. <hi>Iſai. 35.8.</hi> The foole ſhall not erre.
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:22966:42"/>
                        <hi>Iohn. 7.17.</hi> If any man will doe his will, he ſhall know of the doctrine whether it be of God, or whether I ſpeak of myſelfe. <hi>Iſai. 32.3, 4.</hi> The eyes of them that ſee ſhall not be dimme, and the eares of them that heare ſhall hearken The heart alſo of the raſh, ſhall understand knowledge.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou thinkeſt of the great myſtery of God manifeſt in the fleſh, and of one divine eſſence, and three perſons, and ſeeſt thy owne inability to conceive of this great God, apply,</hi> They ſhall all know the Lord. The heart of the ſoole ſhall underſtand.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When wee feare, God will not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veale his will to us, apply,</hi> I will powre out my mind to you. Hee will teach the humble his wayes. He will teach him the way he ſhall chuſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If thou feareſt that though God reveale his will, yet thy ignorance is ſuch, as thou ſhalt not bee able to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand it, apply,</hi> I will cauſe you to
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:22966:43"/>understand. Thou ſhalt understand judgement, righteouſneſſe, equity, and every good path.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If thou feareſt, men will draw thee away to errour, apply,</hi> Counſell ſhall preſerve thee, and understanding ſhall keep thee, and deliver thee from the evill way, and from the man that ſpeaketh froward things, and from them that leave the wayes of righteouſneſſe, to walke in the wayes of darkneſſe. The fooles ſhall not erre. He ſhall know the doctrine whether it be of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="34" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXXIV. LEGACY.</hi> If thou deſireſt grace and art not ſatisfied.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou deſireſt Grace, and thy de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires are not ſatisfied, apply, Pſame
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:22966:43"/>35.7.</hi> Delight thy ſelfe alſo in the Lord, and he ſhall give thee the deſires of thy heart.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 145.19.</hi> He will fulfill the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires of them that feare him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſ. 81.10.</hi> Open thy mouth wide, and I will fill it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Matth. 5.6.</hi> Bleſsed are they which doe hunger and thirſt after righteouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse, for they ſhall be filled.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prov. 10.24.</hi> The deſire of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall be granted.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Doſt thou deſire grace? feareſt thou God will not grant thy deſires? ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> He ſhall give thee thy hearts deſire, he will fulfill thy deſire.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Feareſt thou that if he give grace, it wil be but a litle, apply,</hi> open thy mouth wide, &amp; I will fill it. Thou ſhalt be filled.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 30.18.</hi> Bleſſed are all they which waite for him. Hee will certainly have mercy upon thee at the voyce of thy cry, when he heareth he will anſwer.</p>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:22966:44"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou beginneſt to faint with waiting, apply,</hi> He will certainly have mercy upon thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="35" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXXV. LEGACY.</hi> If thine heart be dead.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou feeleſt thy heart dead, that it will not ſtirre to God or goodneſſe, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Pſal. 22.26. <hi>Your heart ſhall live for ever.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Prov. 3.21.22. <hi>Keep ſound wiſdome and diſcretion, ſo ſhall they be life unto thy ſoule.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 57.15. <hi>I dwell in the high and holy place, with him alſo that is of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite and humble ſpirit, to revive the ſpirit of the humble, and to revive the heart of contrite ones.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:22966:44"/>
                     <p>Amos 5.4. <hi>Seeke the Lord and yee ſhall live.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou feareſt thou ſhalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver overcome the deadneſſe of thy heart, apply, <hi>Your heart ſhall live. Seek the Lord and ye ſhall live.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou haſt got ſome life, and feareſt the looſing of it, apply, <hi>Your hearts ſhall live for ever.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="36" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXXVI. LEGACY.</hi> Jf thou feareſt falling away.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou feareſt thou ſhalt fall away, and beginneſt to decline, apply, 1. Cor. 1.8.</hi> Christ ſhall alſo confirme you unto the end, that ye may be blameleſſe in the day of our Lord Ieſus Chriſt. <hi>Pſal. 16.8.</hi> I have ſet the Lord alwayes before me:
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:22966:45"/>becauſe he is at my right hand, I ſhall not be moved. <hi>Pſal. 145.14.</hi> The Lord upholdeth all that fall: and raiſeth up all thoſe that be bowed down. <hi>Pſal. 91.12.14.</hi> The righteous ſhall flouriſh like the Palmetree. Hee ſhall grow like a Ce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dar in <hi>Lebanon.</hi> They ſhall still bring forth fruit in old age: they ſhall be fat and flouriſhing. <hi>Pſal. 1.13.</hi> And he ſhall be like a tree planted by the rivers of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, that bringeth forth his fruit in his ſeaſon: his leafe alſo ſhall not wither. <hi>Pſ. 31.24.</hi> He ſhall ſtabliſh thine heart. <hi>Iob. 11.15.27.</hi> Thou ſhalt be ſtedfaſt, thine age ſhall be clearer then the noone day, thou ſhalt ſhine forth, thou ſhalt bee as the morning. <hi>Iudg. 5.31.</hi> They that love the lord ſhall bee as the Sunne, when it goeth forth in his might. <hi>Now wee ſee that nothing can hinder the Sun in his might, but it chaſeth away the darkneſſe and clouds before it, and ceaſeth not till it hath runne his race:
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:22966:45"/>ſo ſhall the child of God, for the Lord hath ſaid it, we need not doubt of it. If thou feareſt thine own weaknes, &amp; the power of temptation, with the ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Satan, apply, That God whoſe power and wiſdome over-reacheth all other, hath ſaid,</hi> He will confirme you to the end. He ſhall ſtabliſh thine heart, thy leafe ſhall not fade. <hi>Art thou hard purſued by ſinne and Satan, apply, that God whoſe power and wiſdome over-reacheth all, he hath ſaid,</hi> He will stabliſh thee. <hi>If thou be ready to fall and faint, apply,</hi> The Lord upholdeth all them that fall, and lifteth up all them that are ready to fall: thou ſhalt not ſlide. <hi>If thou feareſt that thou bee kept from ſinne, yet thy graces ſhall decay, apply,</hi> The righteous ſhall flouriſh as a Palme tree, and ſhall grow as a Cedar in <hi>Lebanon.</hi> They ſhall bring forth fruit in their age, they ſhall be fat and flouriſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; thou ſhalt bring forth fruit in ſea
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:22966:46"/>ſon: thou ſhalt bee ſtable, thine age ſhall appeare more cleare than noone day. Thou ſhalt ſhine as the morning.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="37" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXXVII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou art fallen.</head>
                     <p>VVHen wee are fallen and feare the Lord will leave us ſo, then apply, Pſal. 55.22. <hi>Caſt thy burden upon the Lord, and he ſhall ſustaine thee: he ſhall never ſuffer the righteous to be moved.</hi> Pſal. 37.24.28. <hi>Though he fall, he ſhall not be utterly cast downe, for the Lord upholdeth him with his hand. For the Lord loveth judgement, &amp; forſaketh not his Saints, they are preſerved for ever.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ier. 32.40. <hi>I will put my feare in their hearts, that they ſhall not depart
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:22966:46"/>from me.</hi> When thou art fallen, and feeleſt a great load of ſinne or miſery upon thee, and no power to unloade thy ſelfe, thy graces ſo weak, that they will not help thee, and therefore thou thinkeſt thy ſtate deſperate, apply, <hi>Though he fall, he ſhall not be caſt off, for the Lord putteth under his hand.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore though ſinne and miſery be never ſo heavy to preſſe thee downe, yet that powerfull hand of God, when thou art at the loweſt, being under thee, ſhall eaſily lift thee up, thou haſt his promiſe, <hi>hee will not ſuffer thee to fall for ever.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="38" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="60" facs="tcp:22966:47"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XXXVIII. LEGACY.</hi> When the Lord hath forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thee.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen the Lord hath forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thee in thine owne fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, and thou feareſt he will not returne againe, apply, Iſa. 54.7, 8, 9, 10.</hi> For a ſmall moment have I forſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken thee: but with great mercies will I gather thee. In a litle wrath I hid my face from thee for a moment; but with everlaſting kindneſse will I have mercy on thee, ſaith the Lord thy Redeemer. For this is as the waters of <hi>Noah</hi> unto me; for as I have ſworne that the waters of <hi>Noah</hi> ſhall no more goe over the earth: ſo have I ſworne that I would not be wroth with thee, nor rebuke thee. For
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:22966:47"/>the Mountaines ſhall depart, and the Hils ſhall be removed: but my kindneſſe ſhall not depart from thee; neither ſhall the covenant of my peace bee removed, ſaith the Lord that hath mercy on thee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gen. 17.7.</hi> I will eſtabliſh my cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant betwixt thee and me, an everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing covenant to be a God unto thee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deut. 31.8.</hi> I will be with thee, I will not faile thee, neither forſake thee, feare not, neither be diſmayed.</p>
                     <p n="1">
                        <hi>1. Kings 6.13.</hi> I will not forſake my people.</p>
                     <p n="2">
                        <hi>2. Chron. 15.2.</hi> The Lord is with you while you be with him.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iob. 8.20.</hi> Behold, God will not cast away a perfect man.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iob 36.5.</hi> Behold, God is mighty, and deſpiſeth not any.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hoſ. 2.19, 20.</hi> I will betroth thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me for ever; yea I will betroth thee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to me in righteouſneſse, and in judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and in loving kindneſſe, and in
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:22966:48"/>mercies. I will even betroth thee unto me in faithfulneſse.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="39" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE</hi> XXXIX <hi>LEGACY.</hi> When thou feeleſt thy vileneſse.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou feeleſt thy vileneſſe, and feareſt, the Lord will loath thee for it, apply, Levit. 26.11. <hi>My ſoule ſhall not abhorre you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hoſea 14.4. <hi>I will love them freely, for mine anger is turned away from them.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Deut. 7.13. <hi>I will love thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iohn 14.21.23. <hi>He that loveth me ſhall be loved of my Father, and I will love him, and will manifeſt my ſelfe to him, my Father will love him, and wee will come unto him, and make our
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:22966:48"/>abode with him.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ier. 32.41. <hi>I will rejoyce over them to doe them good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou ſeeſt a multitude of ſinnes, ſo that thou ſeemeſt moſt loath<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, apply, <hi>My ſoule ſhall not loath you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou ſeeſt nothing in thy ſelfe that ſhould move him to love thee, but all to the contrary, apply,</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I will love them freely.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thou feareſt thy many ſinnes will cauſe the Lord not to delight in thee, apply, <hi>I will delight in thee.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thou feareſt, thy ſinne will cauſe the Lord to hide himſelfe from thee, apply, <hi>I will ſhew mine owne ſelfe unto him.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="40" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="64" facs="tcp:22966:49"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XL. LEGACY.</hi> When thou feeleſt thy ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall poverty.</head>
                     <p>VVHen thou feeleſt thy ſpirituall poverty, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Matth. 5.3. <hi>Bleſſed are the poore in ſpirit; for theirs is the Kingdome of Heaven.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſa. 66.2. <hi>To him will I look, ſaith the Lord, that is poore and of a contrite ſpirit, and trembleth at my words.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou feeleſt thy ſinnes ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, and thy graces very litle, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore feareſt that ſuch a miſerable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture as thou art, ſhalt not inherit hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, apply, <hi>Bleſſed are the poore in ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for theirs is the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="65" facs="tcp:22966:49"/>
                     <p>If thou feareh the Lord will not looke upon thee, apply, <hi>To him will</hi> I <hi>looke, ſaith the Lord, that is of a con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trite ſpirit.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="41" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XLI. LEGACY.</hi> When thou art in a ſtrait.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou art in a ſtrait, and knoweſt not what to chuſe, either in ſome truth, or in ſomething that is to be done, that thou knoweſt not what to chuſe, apply, Pſal. 25.22.</hi> Him ſhall he teach in the way that he ſhall chuſe. <hi>verſ. 13.</hi> His ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prov. 3.6.</hi> In all thy wayes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge him, and he ſhall direct thy paths.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prov. 16.3.</hi> Commit thy works unto the Lord, and thy thoughts ſhall bee
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:22966:50"/>eſiabliſhed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 30.21.</hi> And thine eare ſhall heare a word behind thee, ſaying, This is the way walke ye in it, when yee turne to the right hand, and when ye turne to the left.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 58.11.</hi> The Lord ſhall guide thee continually.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 61.8. I</hi> will cauſe their worke in truth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ier. 31.9. I</hi> will cauſe them to walke by the rivers of waters, in a ſtraight way wherein they ſhall not ſtumble.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou doubt'ſt of ſome truth, apply,</hi> He ſhall teach him the way that hee ſhall chuſe, his ſoule ſhall dwell at eaſe, Thine eares ſhall heare a voice be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind thee, ſaying, this is the way walke in it. <hi>I</hi> will direct thy way in truth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou art thinking what courſe to take, and feareſt thou ſhalt not know what the Lord would have thee to doe, apply,</hi> Thy thoughts ſhall
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:22966:50"/>be derected, he ſhall direct thy wayes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou feareſt thy weakeneſſe will at ſome times carry thee aſtray, apply,</hi> The Lord will guide thee conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually. The Lord will lead thee in a straight way, that thou ſhalt not stum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="42" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XLII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou fearest Satan will cauſe thee to fall.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou feareſt that Satan by his power and ſubtilty will cauſe thee to fall, and art troubled with his temptations, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Gen. 3.15.</hi> He ſhall bruiſe his head, <hi>Therefore feare not, for Chriſt hath overthrowne all his power and ſubtil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, that he cannot doe us any harme.
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:22966:51"/>Pſal. 19.3, 4.</hi> Surely hee ſhall deliver thee from the ſnare of the fowler. He ſhall cover thee with his feathers: and under his wings ſhalt thou trust: his truth ſhall be thy Shield and Buckler.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Rom. 16.20.</hi> The God of peace ſhall bruiſe Satan under your feet ſhortly.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Doth Satan preſſe thee with ſtrong temptations, and feareſt thou his pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er? apply,</hi> He ſhall bruiſe his head. Hee will cover thee under his wings, and thou ſhalt be ſafe under his feathers, his ſtrength ſhall be thy Buckler.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Feareſt thou his ſubtilty? apply,</hi> Hee ſhall deliver thee from the ſnare of the Fowler, and bruiſe his head, <hi>wherein lyes all his power and plots.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="43" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:22966:51"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XLIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou canſt not profit by the word God.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou canſt not profit by the word of God, or his works of mercy, or afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, apply, Iſai. 48.17. <hi>I am the Lord thy God which teacheth thee to profit, which leadeth thee by the way that thou ſhould goe.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Mat. 21.41. <hi>The Kingdome of God ſhall be taken from you, and given to a Nation bringing forth fruits thereof.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is a promiſe, that the Gentiles ſhall bring forth the fruits of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pell, therefore every believing Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile may apply it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="44" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:22966:52"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XLIV. LEGACY.</hi> If thou findeſt thy ſelfe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like Gods people.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou findeſt thy ſelfe not like the people of God, either in heart or life, apply, Ier. 32.39. <hi>I will give them one heart, and one way.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou ſeeſt thine heart not like the people of God, either in their af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection to God, or his people, or ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, or in their ſorrowing for ſinne, apply, <hi>I will give them one heart.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou ſeeſt thy life and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation not ſo holy as the people of God, apply, <hi>I will give them one way.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="45" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="71" facs="tcp:22966:52"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XLV. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wouldſt have Gods bleſsing rest upon thee.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou wouldſt have the bleſſing of the Lord to reſt upon thee, apply, Pſalme 5.12.</hi> The Lord will bleſse the righteous.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deut. 7.13.</hi> I will bleſse thee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſalme 3.8.</hi> Thy bleſsing is upon thy people.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 24.5.</hi> He ſhall receive the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sing from the Lord, and righteouſneſse from the God of his ſalvation.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 115.12.13.</hi> The Lord will bleſse us, be will bleſse the houſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> hee will bleſſe the houſe of <hi>Aaron.</hi> Hee will bleſſe them that feare the Lord, both ſmall and great.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="46" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:22966:53"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XLVI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou would'ſt be a blesſing in thy place.</head>
                     <p>IF thou would'ſt be a bleſſing in thy place, apply, Gen. 12.2. <hi>I will bleſse thee, and thou ſhalt be a bleſsing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ezek. 34.26. <hi>I will make them about my hill a bleſsing.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="47" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XLVII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou ſeparateſt from the wicked in their corrupt worſhip.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou ſeparateſt thy ſelf from the wicked in their
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:22966:53"/>corrupt worſhip and manners, apply, 2. Cor. 6.16, 17, 18.</hi> I will dwell in them, and walke in them, and <hi>I</hi> will be their God, and they ſhall be my people: Wherefore come out from among them, and be ye ſeparate, ſaith the Lord; and touch not the uncleane thing, and I will receive you; and will be a Father unto you; and ye ſhall be my ſonnes and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, ſaith the Lord Almighty.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thus farre of Grace; the next Promiſes are about the meanes of Grace, either ordinary, or extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="48" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:22966:54"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XLVIII. LEGACY</hi> A promiſe to be applyed in every ordinance.</head>
                     <p>IN every Ordinance thou maiſt ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply this promiſe, Iſai. 12.3. <hi>With joy ſhall you draw water out of the wels of ſalvation.</hi> Now in that it is ſaid, out of the Wels of ſalvation, and not Well, I thinke we ought to apply it to every ordinance of God, ſo as wee are to uſe them with a comfortable per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion, that wee ſhall receive abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance of grace from them. As the Lord promiſeth we ſhall draw waters from out of them, wee ſhall not only uſe them, but draw from them with joy. Therefore when we pray, medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, heare, conferre, faſt, in every du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:22966:54"/>apply this promiſe, and you ſhall find him faithfull which promiſeth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="49" type="legacy">
                     <head>THE XLIX. LEGACY. <hi>When thou prayeſt.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou prayeſt apply theſe promiſes for the ſtrengthening of thy faith, and for thy hearing. Mat. 7.7.</hi> Aske, and it ſhall be given you, ſeek and you ſhall find, knock and it ſhall be opened unto you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mat. 6.6.</hi> Pray to the Father which ſeeth in ſecret, and thy Father which ſeeth in ſecret, ſhall reward the openly.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mat. 21, 22.</hi> And all things whatſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ye ſhall aske in prayer, believing ye ſhall receive it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iohn 14.13, 14.</hi> Whatſoever ye ſhall
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:22966:55"/>aske in my name I will doe it.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Ioh. 16.24.</hi> Aske and ye ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive, that your joy may be full.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iohn 15.7.</hi> Aske what you will, and it ſhall done unto you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 65.24.</hi> Before they call, I will anſwer, and while they are yet ſpeaking, I will heare.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iob 22.7.</hi> Thou ſhalt make thy pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers unto him, and he ſhall heare thee, and if thou ſeek him, he will be found.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="50" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE L. LEGACY.</hi> WHen thou meditateſt.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou meditateſt, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply theſe promiſes, Prov. 14.22. <hi>Mercy and truth ſhall be to them that deviſe good.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Pſal. 103.17, 18. <hi>The loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:22966:55"/>of the Lord endureth for ever, to them which think upon his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments to doethem.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Philip. 4.8, 9. <hi>Thinke on theſe things, which ye have both learned, and received, and heard, and ſeene in me, and the God of peace ſhall be with you.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thou deſireſt mercy, or the truth of God to be forthy good, or the lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving kindeſſe of the Lord to bee for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver towards thee, and that God which brings peace with him, to be with thee, then meditate on good things, &amp; with ſuch a meditation, as may ſtirre thee up to practiſe, &amp; the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> all theſe promiſes ſhall ſurely be performed to thee. And becauſe meditation is an hard duty, therefore encourage thy ſelfe to it by the benefit it brings, and it being a way of God, he will give thee his Spirit to cauſe thee to walke in it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="51" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="78" facs="tcp:22966:56"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LI. LEGACY.</hi> In meditating, conferring, and reading Gods word.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN meditating, conferring, and rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the word of God, apply, Ioſh. 1.8.</hi> Let not this booke of the Law depart out of thy mouth, but medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate therein day and night, that thou maiſt obſerve to doe according to all that is written therein: for then thou ſhalt make thy way proſperous, and then thou ſhalt have good ſucceſſe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="52" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="79" facs="tcp:22966:56"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE. LII. LEGACY.</hi> In reading of the word of thou understandeſt not.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN reading of the word, if wee un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand not, apply theſe promiſes, Prov. 1.23.</hi> I will powre out my Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit unto you, I will make knowne my words unto you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prov. 1.4.</hi> It gives ſubtilty to the ſimple: to the young men knowledge and diſcretion.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 19.8.</hi> The Commandement of the Lord is pure, inlightning the eyes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="53" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="80" facs="tcp:22966:57"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou canſt not conferre.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou canſt not ſpeake in conference to edification, but feeleſt thine heart ſhut up, then apply, Iohn 7.38. <hi>He that be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieveth on me, out of his belly ſhall flow rivers of living water.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Prov. 10.31. <hi>The mouth of the juſt bringeth forth wiſdome.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Prov. 12.14. <hi>A man ſhall be ſatisfied with good by the fruit of his mouth.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 32.4. <hi>The tongue of the stamme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers ſhall be ready to ſpeake plainly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 35.6. <hi>The dumbe mans tongue ſhall ſing.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou art with the people of God, that thou maiſt receive good
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:22966:57"/>from them, and doe them good, apply, Prov. 13.20. <hi>He that walketh with wiſe men ſhall be wiſe.</hi> So apply, Prov. 12.14. Iohn. 7.38. Ezek. 47.12. <hi>His fruit ſhall be meat, and his leaves medicine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thou findeſt thy ſoule ſtand in need of wiſdome, keep company with the people of God which are the only wiſe people, and then thou haſt the only ſure promiſes of the Lord, thou ſhalt bee wiſe. If thou hungreſt after good, reſort to the righteous, and thou ſhalt bee ſatisfied with good things. If thou feele thy ſelfe dead, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>out of him ſhall flow rivers of water of life,</hi> for thy quickning. If thy ſoule be faint or ſicke, apply, <hi>His fruit ſhall be meant and his leave medicine.</hi> Let all this good which is gotten by their fellowſhip cauſe thee to delight in them, and take heed of forſaking the fellowſhip of the Saints.</p>
                     <p>When thou goeſt into company,
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:22966:58"/>apply theſe promiſes to thy ſelfe, that thou maiſt be ſo to others, and hinder not thy ſelfe, by unbeliefe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="54" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LIV. LEGACY.</hi> When thou art to goe to the asſemblies.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou art to goe to the aſſemblies, to partici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pate in the ordinances, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> In places where I record my name, I will come to thee and bleſſe thee. <hi>If thou wanteſt the Lord, or his bleſſing, goe to his houſe, and thou ſhalt find him Pſalme 36.8, 9.</hi> They ſhall be abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly ſatisfied with the fatneſſe of thine houſe, and thou ſhalt make them drinke of the river of thy pleaſures. For with thee is the fountaine of life, and in
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:22966:58"/>thy light ſhall we ſee light. <hi>Pſ. 65.4.</hi> We ſhall be ſatisfied with the geodneſſe of thy houſe, even of thine holy Temple. <hi>Pſalme 83.11.</hi> The Lord God is a Sun and ſhield, the Lord will give grace and glory, and no good thing will he with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold. <hi>Pſalme 92.13.14.</hi> Thoſe that he planted in the houſe of the Lord, ſhall flouriſh in the courts of our God. They ſhall ſtill bring forth fruit in their old age: they ſhall bee fat and flouriſhing. <hi>Pſalme 128.5.</hi> The Lord ſhall bleſse thee out of <hi>Sion. Iſai. 25.6, 7, 8.</hi> In this mountain ſhall the Lord of Hoſts make unto all people a feaſt of fat things, a feaſt of wine on the lees, of fat things full of marrow, of wines on the lees, well refined. <hi>Therefore when his or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances are corrupted with mens in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ventions, then thou maiſt preſſe him with this promiſe, that he will give us wine fined and purified, even his pureſt ordinances, and moſt comfortable to
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:22966:59"/>our hearts, as wine is. And when there is litle nouriſhment, becauſe their gifts are weake, urge him with this, that he hath promiſed to make us a feaſt of fat things full of marrow; for I take this promiſe to be meant of the Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches after Chriſt, verſ. 7.</hi> And he will deſtroy in this mountain the face of the covering caſt over all people, and the the vaile that is ſpread over all nations. <hi>Thy ſins that are too ſtrong for thee, bring them to the Lord in his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and he will deſtroy them, though thou ſeeme to be covered with them, and they ſpread as a vaile upon thee, yet believe his promiſes, and all things ſhall be poſſible unto thee. Iſai. 57.7.</hi> I will make them joyfull in mine houſe of prayer, their ſacrifices ſhal be accepted at mine Altar. <hi>God will both give to them and accept from their ſacrifices, as pleaſing to him. 2. Chro. 20.20.</hi> Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieve his Prophets, ſo ſhall ye proſper.</p>
                     <pb n="85" facs="tcp:22966:59"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prov. 1.5.</hi> A wiſe man will heare, and will encreaſe learning, and a man of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derstanding ſhall attaine unto wiſe counſels. <hi>Prov. 4.10.12.</hi> Heare and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive my ſayings, and the yeares of thy life ſhall be many, when thou goeſt, thy ſteps ſhall not be ſtrait, and when thou runneſt, thou ſhalt not ſtumble. <hi>Mark. 4.24.</hi> Vnto you that have, ſhall more be given. <hi>Iſai. 55.3.11, 12.</hi> Incline your eares and come unto me, heare and your ſoules ſhall live; and I will make an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verlasting Covenant with you, even the ſure mercies of <hi>David.</hi> My words ſhall accompliſh that which I pleaſe, and it ſhall proſper in the thing whereto I ſent it. Therefore ye ſhall goe forth with joy, and be led forth with peace; the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines and the hils ſhall bread forth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore you into ſinging, and all the trees of the field ſhall clap their hands. <hi>verſ. 13.</hi> Inſtead of the thorne ſhall come up the Firre tree, and inſtead of the bryer ſhall
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:22966:60"/>come up the Mirtle tree: <hi>this force ſhall the word have in thine heart for planting of Grace, and deſtroying of ſinne.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hoſ. 14.7.</hi> They that dwell under his ſhadow ſhall returne, they ſhall revive as the corne, and grow as the vine, the ſent thereof ſhall be as the vine in <hi>Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>banon. If thou wouldſt returne, apply this,</hi> he ſhall returne. <hi>If thou beeſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cayed, apply this;</hi> They ſhall revive as the corne. <hi>If thou wouldeſt flouriſh in grace, apply,</hi> They ſhall flouriſh as the Vine. <hi>If thou wouldeſt bee a ſweet ſmelling ſavour in all places, apply,</hi> The ſent thereof ſhall be as the Vine of <hi>Lebanon. Seeing all theſe good things come from the powerfull ordinances of the Lord, let us give him no reſt, till he beſtow theſe bleſſings upon us; when the Paſtour of the people pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nounceth the bleſſing, apply this pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, Num. 6.27.</hi> I will bleſſe thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="55" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="87" facs="tcp:22966:60"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LV. LEGACY.</hi> Wouldeſt thou enjoy the ordinances of God, and a bleſſing upon them.</head>
                     <p>WOuldeſt thou enjoy the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances of God, and a bleſſing upon them, apply, Ier. 31.14. <hi>I will ſatiate the ſoules of the Prieſts with fatneſse, and my people ſhall be ſatisfied with goodneſse.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ier. 3.15. <hi>I will give you Pastours according to mine heart, which ſhall feed you with knowledge and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ezek. 34.26, 27. <hi>And I will make them and the places round about my hill a bleſsing, and I will cauſe the ſhowre to come downe in his ſeaſon: there ſhall bee ſhowers of bleſsing. And the tree of the
<pb n="88" facs="tcp:22966:61"/>field ſhall yield her encreaſe, and the earth ſhall yield her fruit.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The promiſes are both for Paſtor and people, the Paſtor ſhall be able to teach with knowledge and underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, his ſoule ſhall bee repleniſhed with fatneſſe, his teaching ſhall bee as ſeaſonable ſhowres of bleſſing, that ſhall make the people fruitfull. The people muſt apply theſe promiſes, firſt that God would give them able Tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, and that they may find their miniſtery bleſſed unto them, accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to theſe promiſes. That they may bee fed with knowledge and under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, that they may bee ſatisfied with goodneſſe, and that their teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing may bee ſeaſonable ſhowers of bleſſing to make them fruitfull, as it is promiſed, that the trees ſhall yield their fruit. How much are Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances to be deſired, by which he doth convey ſo many bleſſings unto his
<pb n="89" facs="tcp:22966:61"/>people? Let us give him no reſt, till he furniſh <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> with all her ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances and officers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="56" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LVI. LEGACY.</hi> Jf thou enjoyest grace or meanes of Grace.</head>
                     <p>IF thou enjoyeſt glorious graces, or meanes of grace, and feareſt the looſing of them, apply, Iſai, 4.5.6. <hi>Vpon all the glory ſhall be a defence. And there ſhall be a Tabernacle for a ſhadow in the day time from the heat, and for a place of refuge, and for a covert from ſtorme, and from raine.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 27.3. <hi>I the Lord doe keep it, I will water it every moment: leaſt any hurt it, I will keep it night and day.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iſai. 33.16. <hi>His place of defence ſhall
<pb n="90" facs="tcp:22966:62"/>be the munition of Rockes, bread ſhall be given him, his waters ſhall be ſure.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Haſt thou any glorious grace or meanes of grace? Arme thy ſelfe with the power of God in his promiſes, for the Devill will ue all his fores and ſubtilty, to deprive thee of them; haſt thou a glorious Miniſter, and pure or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance, or glorious graces beginne to ſpring in thine heart, and ſeeſt no meanes to defend them? apply, <hi>Vpon all thy glory he ſhall be a defence. His de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence ſhall bee a munition of Rockes.</hi> Seeſt thou an heart of ſinne in thy ſelf, or the rage of the wicked, that cauſeth thee to feare the loſſe of them? apply, <hi>There ſhall be a covering for a ſhadow in the day for the heat.</hi> Doth the Devill raiſe up ſtormes? inwardly perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons? apply, <hi>The defence and covering ſhall be a place of refuge, and covert for the ſtorme, and for the raine.</hi> Feareſt thou the ſubtilty of thine enemies,
<pb n="91" facs="tcp:22966:62"/>that unawares when thou thinkeſt not on them, they will ſurpriſe thee, and ſteale thy bleſſing from thee? apply, I <hi>the Lord doe keepe it night and day.</hi> If thou feareſt God will not continue thus to thee, apply. <hi>I will water it eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment;</hi> not one moment, but hee will be adding and nouriſhing: <hi>Bread ſhall be given him, and his waters ſhall be ſure.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="57" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LVII. LEGACY.</hi> When thou art baniſhed from Gods ordinances.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou art baniſhed from Gods ordinances, apply theſe promiſes for thy re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne, Iſai. 35.10.</hi> The ranſomed of the Lord ſhall return and come to <hi>Sion</hi> with
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:22966:63"/>ſongs, and everlasting joy upon their heads: they ſhall obtaine joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and ſorrow and ſighing ſhall flee away. <hi>Ier. 3.14.</hi> I will take you two of a family, and one of a Citty, and will bring you to <hi>Sion. Deut. 30.4.</hi> If any of thine be driven out to the utmost parts of hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, from thence will the Lord thy God gather thee, and from thence will hee fetch thee. <hi>Ezek. 34.11, 12, 13.14, 15, 16.</hi> Behold I, even <hi>I</hi> will both ſearch my ſheep and ſeek them out. As a Sheepheard ſeeketh out his flock in the day that he is among his Sheep that are ſcattered: ſo will <hi>I</hi> ſeek out my Sheep, and will deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver them out of all places, where they have been ſcattered in the cloudy and darke day. And <hi>I</hi> will bring them out from the people, and gather them from the people, and gather them from the countries, and will bring them to their owne land, and feed them upon the mountaines of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> by the rivers, and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:22966:63"/>in all the inhabited places of the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tre<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                        <hi>I</hi> will feed them in a good paſture, and upon the high mountaines of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſhall their fold he: there ſhall they lye in a good fold, &amp; in a fat paſture ſhall they feed upon the mountaines of <hi>Iſrael.</hi> I will ſeed my flock, &amp; I wil cauſe them to lye down, ſaith the Lord God. <hi>I</hi> will ſeek that which was loſt, and bring againe that which was driven away, and will bind up that which was broken, and will strengthen that which was ſick.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If thou mourneſt for Gods ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt not onely re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne to <hi>Sion,</hi> but returne with joy, and ſorrow ſhall flye away. <hi>If thou beeſt but one amongſt many which deſireſt it, and feareſt thou ſhalt bee left among them, apply,</hi> I will take you, one of a cit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and two of a Tribe: <hi>though thou beeſt but one of a City that returneth to the Lord, he will bring thee to</hi> Sion <hi>from all the reſt. If thou art farre re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:22966:64"/>from all meanes, and that the Lord hath done it for thy ſin, apply,</hi> Though thou wert cast into the out most part of the Heaven, thence will the Lord gather thee, and from thence will the Lord gather thee, &amp; from thence wil he take thee; he will deliver them from all places where they have been ſcattered in the cloudy and darke day, and will feed them in good paſtures, and will bring them to rest.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="58" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LVIII. LEGACY.</hi> Whilſt thou art baniſh't from Gods houſe.</head>
                     <p>WHilſt thou art baniſhed from Gods houſe, apply, Ezek. 11.16. <hi>I will be unto them as a litle Sanctuary in the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:22966:64"/>where they ſhall come.</hi> Iſai. 40.11. <hi>He ſhall feed his flock like a ſheepheard he ſhall gather the Lambes with his arme, and carry them in his boſome, and ſhall gently lead thoſe that are with young.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In thy baniſhment, at thoſe houres when thy ſoule was wont to be refre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed in the Sanctuary of God on the Sabbath, and at other times when thou findeſt thy ſelfe to ſtand in need either of defence, or nouriſhment, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, I <hi>will be a Sanctuary unto you. He ſhall feed his flock as a ſheepheard.</hi> If in this time thou feeleſt thy ſelfe very weake, apply. <hi>He ſhall gather his Lambs in his armes, and carry them in his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome, and guide them with young:</hi> they cannot miſcarry that are ſhut up in the boſome of God, nor feare, who are guided by him. Therefore though we be never ſo weake in our ſelves, yet here is our comfort, we are ſafe in our
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:22966:65"/>God: O happy people, ſaved by the Lord.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="59" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LIX. LEGACY.</hi> When wicked ſheepheards are over us.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen wicked ſheepheards are over us, then apply, Eze. 34.10.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold, I am againſt the ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards, and I will require my flock at their hands, and cauſe them to ceaſe from feeding the flock: neither ſhall the ſheepheards feed themſelves any more. for I will deliver my flock from their mouth, that they may not be meat for them. <hi>verſ. 21.22.</hi> Becauſe ye have thruſt with ſide, and with ſhoulder, and puſht all the diſeaſed with your hornes, till yee
<pb n="97" facs="tcp:22966:65"/>have ſcattered them abroad: Therefore will I ſave my flock, and they ſhall no more be a prey, and I will cauſe the wild beasts to ceaſe out of the land.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When the ſheepheards feed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, and are ready to devoure us, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> The ſheepheards ſhall not feed them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves any more. I will deliver my ſheep from their mouthes, they ſhall no more devoure them.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When through their greatneſſe and our weakneſſe, they puſh us ſo with their hornes, that wee are ſcattered, both ſheepheard from people, and one from another, apply,</hi> I will help my ſheep, and they ſhall no more be ſpoyled; I will cauſe the wild beaſts to ceaſe out of the land.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="60" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="98" facs="tcp:22966:66"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LX. LEGACY.</hi> When through wicked ſheepheards thou art come to great miſery.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen through evill ſheep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heards we are come to great miſery, apply, Ezek. 34.16.</hi> I will ſeek that which was lost, and bring again that which was driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way, and will bind up that which was broken, and will ſtrengthen that which was ſick. <hi>Iſai. 30.20.</hi> Though the Lord give you the bread of adverſity, and the water of affliction, yet ſhall not thy tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers bee removed into a corner any more, but thine eyes ſhall ſee thy teachers. <hi>When through evill ſheepheards thou art come to ſuch an eſtate as thou fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſt thy ſelfe to have loſt God and
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:22966:66"/>goodneſſe, and art driven away from all things that might help thee, apply,</hi> I will ſeek that which was lost, I will bring again that which was driven a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. <hi>When thou art even broken with miſery, and growne very weak, apply,</hi> I will bind up that which was broken, and ſtrengthen that which was weake. <hi>When thy Teachers which ſhould help thee in this eſtate, are forced to flye and hide themſelves for feare of wicked ſheepheards, apply,</hi> Thy teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſhall not bee removed into a corner any more, but thine eyes ſhall ſee thy Teachers.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Thus farre of the ordinances of God, which are ordinary; Now for the duty of Faſting, which is extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="61" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:22966:67"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXI. LEGACY.</hi> When thou ſettest thy ſelfe to fast.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou ſetteſt thy ſelfe to faſt, apply, Matth. 6.18. <hi>If thou faſt in ſecret, thy Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther wich ſeeth in ſecret will reward thee openly.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Iam. 4.8.10. <hi>Draw nigh unto God, and he will draw nigh unto you. Hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble your ſelves in the ſight of the Lord and he ſhall lift you up.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus farre of the meanes of Grace. The next promiſes are when wee ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer perſecution for well-doing, for all that will live godly muſt ſuffer perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cution: therefore ſtrengthen thy ſelfe with theſe promiſes.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="62" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="101" facs="tcp:22966:67"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou art railed upon for well-doing.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou art railed upon for well-do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, apply, 1. Pet. 4.14.</hi> If yee be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proached for the name of Chriſt, happy are ye, for the Spirit of God, and of glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſteth upon you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Mat. 5.11, 12.</hi> Bleſsed are yee, when men revile you, and perſecute you, and ſhall ſay all manner of evill againſt you falſely for my ſake. Rejoyce and be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding glad, for great is your reward in heaven, for ſo perſecuted they the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets which were before you.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="63" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:22966:68"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou are perſecuted.</head>
                     <p>WHen they perſecute thee any other wayes even unto death, apply, Mat. 10.39. <hi>He that looſeth his life for my ſake, ſhall find it.</hi> Matth. 5.10. <hi>Bleſsed are they which are perſecuted for righteouſneſſe ſake: for theirs is the Kingdome of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> When we looſe any earthly bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing for Gods cauſe, apply, Matth. 19.24. <hi>Every one that hath forſaken hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or brethren, or ſiſters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my names ſake, ſhall receive an hundred fold, and ſhall inherit everlaſting life.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>This is the greateſt (and yet law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full) uſury of all others, to part with
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:22966:68"/>one outward bleſſing, and to receive an hundred for it; to looſe a miſerable life, and to enjoy eternall life; to ſuffer a ſhort time, and to have a great reward in heaven; to be diſgraced, and to have the Spirit of glory reſt upon us. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when thou art railed upon, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>Bleſsed am I, the Spirit of glory reſts upon me, therefore they cannot make me vile.</hi> Art thou any way perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted? apply, <hi>Theirs is the Kingdome of Heaven; great is your reward in Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Take they thy life? apply, <hi>He that looſeth his life for my ſake ſhall find it.</hi> Take they away any earthly bleſſing? thou ſhalt receive an hundreth fold at this preſent; therefore if Uſurers glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly let out their money, that hope to receive but eight in the hundreth, bee aſhamed of thy ſelfe, that thou ſhouldſt not give one for an hundreth, when thou haſt the promiſe of him that never failed to performe.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="64" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:22966:69"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXIV. LEGACY.</hi> Jn partaking with Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in ſuffering.</head>
                     <p>IN partaking with Gods people in ſuffering, that thou maiſt be parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of their comforts, apply, 1. Cor. 1.6. <hi>As you are partakers of the ſufferings: ſo ſhall ye be alſo of the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolation.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="65" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXV. LEGACY.</hi> When thou art called to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend the truth.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou art called forth to defend the truth, apply, Matth. 10.19.</hi> When they
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:22966:69"/>deliver you up, take no thought, how, or what ye ſhall ſpeak, for it ſhall be given you in that ſame houre what yee ſhall ſpeake.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Luke 21.15.</hi> I will give you a mouth and wiſdome which all your adverſaries ſhall not bee able to gaineſay nor reſist. <hi>Math. 10.32.</hi> Whoſoever confeſſeth me before men, him will I confeſse before my Father which is in heaven. <hi>When thou feareſt thou ſhalt not be able to ſpeake in defence of the truth, apply,</hi> It ſhall be given thee, though thou haſt it not before, in that houre, what thou ſhalt ſay. <hi>If thou feareſt the learning of thine adverſaries, and thine owne ſimple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, apply, I</hi> will give the not onely a mouth, but alſo wiſdome, where-againſt they ſhall not be able to ſpeake. <hi>If thou want courage, embolden thy ſelfe with this, Chriſt will confeſſe thee be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his father.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="66" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:22966:70"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXVI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wouldeſt bring forth ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable fruit for every eſtate.</head>
                     <p>IF thou wouldſt bring forth ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable fruit for every eſtate, and for every duty, apply, Pſal. 1.3. <hi>Thou ſhalt as a tree which bringeth forth his fruit in ſeaſon.</hi> Ezek. 47.12. <hi>Hee ſhall bring forth fruit according to his moneths.</hi> If thou art to ſpeake or pray, or doe any duty, that thou maiſt doe it ſeaſonably, and have fitting words and thoughts, apply, <hi>Thou ſhalt bring forth fruit in ſeaſon.</hi> So in every eſtate, proſperity or adverſity, that thou maiſt bring forth the fruits of it, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, <hi>They ſhall bring forth fruit in ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon according to their moneths.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="107" facs="tcp:22966:70"/>
                     <p>Thus farre about ſpirituall things. The next promiſes, are about earthly things: and becauſe Children are the moſt excellent, therefore I will begin with them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="67" type="legacy">
                     <head>THE LXVII. LEGACY.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou haſt children, apply, Pſ. 112.2.</hi> His ſeed ſhall be mighty upon earth: the generation of the juſt ſhall be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deut. 7.13.</hi> He will bleſſe the fruit of thy womb. <hi>Gen. 17.7.</hi> I will establiſh my covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee, in their generations for an everlaſting covenant, to be a God unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee. <hi>Iſai. 44.3.4.</hi> I will powre out my Spirit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="108" facs="tcp:22966:71"/>on thy ſeed, and my bleſsing upon thine off ſpring: and they ſhall ſpring up as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the graſse, as willowes by the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter-courſes. <hi>If thou deſireſt grace and Gods bleſſing for thy children, apply, I</hi> will powre my ſpirit and bleſsing upon thy ſeed. <hi>If thou wouldeſt have them grow up in it, apply,</hi> They ſhall grow as among the graſse, and as the willowes by the water courſes. <hi>If thou wouldeſt have them in covenant with thy ſelfe, thy God to be theirs, apply, I</hi> will make an everlaſting covenant with thee, to be God to thee, and to thy ſeed after thee. <hi>Deſireſt thou outward things for them? apply,</hi> His ſeed ſhall bee mighty upon earth.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="68" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="109" facs="tcp:22966:71"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXVIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wanteſt children.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou wanteſt children, apply, Deut. 7.14.</hi> Thou ſhalt be bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed above all people, there ſhall nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther be male nor female barren among you. <hi>Deut.</hi> 28.11. The Lord ſhall make thee plentifull in the fruit of thy body. <hi>Pſal. 128.3.</hi> Thy wife ſhall be as a fruit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Vine by the ſides of thine houſe, thy children like Olive plants, round about thy table. <hi>verſ. 4.6.</hi> Loe thus ſhall the man be bleſſed that feareth the Lord. Thou ſhalt ſee thy childrens children.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If thou haſt conceived, apply this promiſe for keeping of it, Exod. 23.26.</hi> There ſhall none caſt their young, nor be barren in thy land. <hi>This, and allo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:22966:72"/>promiſes of earthly things, are to to be applyed ſo farre as is good for us: we are not to doubt of them.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="69" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXIX. LEGACY.</hi> If the Lord deny thee children.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF the Lord deny thee children, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Iſai. 56.5.</hi> To them will I give mine houſe, and within my walls a place and a name better then of Sonnes and of Daughters, I will give them an everlaſting name that ſhall not be cut off.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="70" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="111" facs="tcp:22966:72"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXX. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wouldſt have a comfortable and holy uſe of thy habitation.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou wouldſt have the comforta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble and holy uſe of thine habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, apply, Iob. 5.24.</hi> Thou ſhalt know that thy Tabernacle ſhall be in peace, and thou ſhalt viſit thine habitation, and not ſinne.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſalme 91.10.</hi> There ſhall no evill befall thee, neither ſhall any plague come nighthy dwelling. <hi>Prov. 14.11.</hi> The Tabernacle of the upright ſhall flouriſh. <hi>Prov. 12.7.</hi> The houſe of the righteous ſhall stand.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If thou wouldſt proſper in thine houſe, apply,</hi> Peace ſhall be in it. No plague ſhall come neer it. It ſhall flouriſh.
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:22966:73"/>
                        <hi>If thou wouldſt have it continue ſo, apply,</hi> It ſhall ſtand. <hi>That they may not be a ſnare to thee, but that thou maiſt uſe thy bleſſing, and not ſinne, apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt viſit thy habitation, and not ſinne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="71" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wouldſt have thy going out, and comming in bleſſed.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou wouldſt have thy comming in and going out bleſſed, apply, Deut. 28.6.</hi> Bleſsed ſhalt thou be when thou commest in, and bleſsed ſhalt thou bee when thou goeſt out, <hi>Pſalme 121.8.</hi> The Lord ſhall pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve thy going out, and thy comming in, from this time forth, and even for evermore.</p>
                     <pb n="113" facs="tcp:22966:73"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou goeſt out, if thou wouldſt have heavens and earth, and all creatures bleſſed to thee, and bee made able to make the ſpirituall uſe of them, apply,</hi> Bleſsed ſhalt thou be when thou goeſt out, and when thou com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mest in. The Lord ſhall preſerve thy go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing out, and thy comming in. <hi>If thou wouldſt have the continuance of it, apply,</hi> from this time forth for ever<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>more.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="72" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXII. LEGACY.</hi> When thou eateſt or enjoyeſt any bleſsing, that it may ſatisfy, and be ſanctified.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou eateſt or enjoyeſt any bleſſing, that it may ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfy, thee and thou maiſt
<pb n="114" facs="tcp:22966:74"/>have the ſanctified uſe of it, apply, Ioel 2.26. <hi>Ye ſhall eat in plenty and be ſatisfied, and praiſe the name of the Lord our God.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That thy meat and outward bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings may give thee content, and ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fy thee, apply, <hi>Thou ſhalt eat and be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tisfied.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That thou maiſt have the ſanctified uſe of it, apply, <hi>Thou ſhalt praiſe the Lord.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="73" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXIII. LEGACY.</hi> When thou takest thy reſt at night, &amp;c.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou takeſt thy reſt at night, apply, Prov. 3.24.</hi> When thou lyeſt downe thou ſhalt not bee afraid: yea thou ſhalt lye
<pb n="115" facs="tcp:22966:74"/>down, and thy ſleep ſhall be ſweet.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iob 11.19.</hi> Alſo thou ſhalt lye down, and none ſhall make thee afraid.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If thou art troubled with feares of the night, apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt not be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou takeſt thy reſt, apply,</hi> None ſhall make thee afraid.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If thou art troubled with any thing that breaks thy reſt, apply,</hi> Thy rest ſhall be ſweet.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="74" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXIV. LEGACY.</hi> When thou putteſt thy hand to any works.</head>
                     <p>WHen thou putteſt thine hand to any worke, that it may be bleſſed, apply, Deut. 28.12. <hi>The Lord ſhall bleſſe all the workof
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:22966:75"/>thine hand.</hi> Deut. 30.9. <hi>The Lord thy God will make thee plentuous in every work of thine hand.</hi> The Lord will not only bleſſe ſome of thy works, but e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one; therefore in every worke ſend up ſhort prayers for the claiming of them, and ſo at our going out, and comming in, or ſleeping, renew theſe promiſes upon thy ſelfe, by faith ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying them, and by prayer ſuing for them.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="75" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LEXXV. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wouldſt have thine out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward bleſsings bleſſed.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou wouldſt have thy outward bleſſings bleſſed of God, apply, Deut. 28.4, 5.</hi> Bleſsed ſhall be the fruit of thy body, and the fruit of thy
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:22966:75"/>ground, and the fruit of thy cattell, the increaſe of thy kine, and the flocks of thy ſheep. Bleſsed ſhall bee thy baſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ket and thy ſtore. <hi>Deut. 7.13.14.</hi> The Lord will alſo bleſse the fruit of thy wombe, and the fruit of thy land, thy corne, and thy wine, and thine oyle, the increaſe of thy kine, and the flocks of thy ſheep. There ſhall be neither male nor fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male barren among you, or among your cattell. <hi>That thy goods and thine houſe may be bleſſed, apply,</hi> Bleſſed ſhall be thy basket and thy store. <hi>If thou beeſt in debt, apply, Deut. 28.12.</hi> Thou ſhalt lend unto many, and ſhalt not borrow.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="76" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="118" facs="tcp:22966:76"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXVI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou deſireſt to enjoy the la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours of thine hands.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou deſireſt to enjoy the labours of thine hands, apply, Iſai. 65.21, 22, 23.</hi> They ſhall build houſes and inhabit them, they ſhall plant vineyards and eat the fruit of them. They ſhall not build, and another inha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit; they ſhall not plant and another eat: for as the dayes of a tree are the dayes of my people, and mine elect ſhall long en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joy the works of their hands. They ſhall not labour in vaine, nor bring forth for trouble. <hi>Pſal. 128.2.</hi> Thou ſhalt eat the labour of thine hands.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="77" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="119" facs="tcp:22966:76"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXVII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou art diligent in thy calling.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou art diligent in thy calling, apply, Prov. 12.14.24.</hi> The recompence of a mans hands ſhall be rendered unto him. The hand of the diligent ſhall beare rule. <hi>When thou enjoyeſt that thou haſt laboured for, apply, Pſalme 128.2.</hi> Thou ſhalt eat the labour of thine hands: happy ſhalt thou be, and it ſhall be well with thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="78" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="120" facs="tcp:22966:77"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXVIII. LEGACY.</hi> When thou ſeest wicked men follow unſatisfying things with reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſse deſires and thou de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſireſt content.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou ſeeſt the wicked to bee carried with reſtleſſe deſires, hungrying and thir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting after thoſe things which ſatisfy them not, and thou deſireſt content, apply, Iſai. 65.13, 14.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord, behold my ſervants ſhall eat, but ye ſhall be hungry; behold my ſervants ſhall drink, but ye ſhall be thirſty, be hold my ſervants ſhall rejoyce, but yee ſhall be aſhamed: Behold my ſervants ſhall ſing for joy of heart, but yee ſhall cry for ſorrow of heart, and ſhall howle for vexation of ſpirit.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="79" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:22966:77"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXIX. LEGACY.</hi> If thou fearest thou ſhalt looſe by following the Lord.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou feareſt thou ſhalt looſe by following the Lord, apply Pſalme 37.9.11.18, 19.</hi> Thoſe that waite up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Lord ſhall inherit the earth, their inheritance ſhall be for ever: they ſhall not be aſhamed in the evill time. They ſhall inherit the earth, and delight them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves in the abundance of peace. <hi>Pſalm. 112.3.</hi> Wealth and riches ſhall bee in his houſe. <hi>Iob. 22, 23, 24.</hi> Thou ſhalt be built up, thou ſhalt lay up gold as duſt, and the gold of Ophir as the stones of of the brookes <hi>verſ. 25.</hi> Yea, the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty ſhall bee thy defence, and thou ſhalt have plenty of ſilver.</p>
                     <pb n="122" facs="tcp:22966:78"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Gen. 15.1.</hi> I am thy exceeding great reward. <hi>Feareſt thou the loſſe of thy land, apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt inherit the earth, their inheritance ſhall be for ever. Thou ſhalt poſſeſſe the earth. <hi>Doe others trouble thee? apply,</hi> They ſhall have their delight in the multitude of peace. <hi>Art thou poore, or feareſt the loſſe of thy goods? apply,</hi> Riches and treaſure ſhall be in his houſe. <hi>Art thou oppreſſed by the wicked? apply,</hi> The Almighty ſhall be thy defence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="80" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXX. LEGACY.</hi> When thou haſt loſt bleſſings by ſinne.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou haſt loſt bleſſings by ſinne, apply theſe promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes for their recovery, Ioel.
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:22966:78"/>2.24, 25, 26.</hi> The floores ſhall be full of Wheat, and he fats ſhall overflow with wine and oyle, and I will reſtore to you the yeares that the Locust hath eaten, the canker-worme, the caterpiller, and the palme-worme: and yee ſhall eat in plenty, and be ſatisfied, and praiſe the Lord. <hi>Deut. 30.5.</hi> I will multiply you a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove your fathers.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="81" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXXI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou feareſt loſſe of thy good name.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou feareſt the loſſe of thy good name, apply, Iob. 5.21.</hi> Thou ſhalt be hid from the ſcourge of the tongue. <hi>Iob. 11.15.</hi> Thou ſhalt lift up thy face without ſpot. <hi>Pſal. 37.6.</hi> He ſhall bring forth thy righteouſneſse as the light, and
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:22966:79"/>thy judgement as the noone day. <hi>Prov. 10.7.</hi> The memory of the juſt is bleſſed.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Feareſt thou the wicked will take away thy good name, apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt bee hid from the ſcourge of the tongue. <hi>Caſt they blots upon thee? apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt lift up thy face without ſpot. <hi>Seek they to darken the light of thy holy life? apply,</hi> He ſhall bring forth thy righteouſneſſe as the light, and thy judgement as the noone day.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="82" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXXII. LEGACY.</hi> If the world deſpiſe thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF the World deſpiſe thee, comfort thy ſelfe with theſe promiſes, Exo. 19.5.</hi> Ye ſhall be Gods peculiar trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure above all people. <hi>1. Sam. 3.30.</hi> Thoſe
<pb n="125" facs="tcp:22966:79"/>that honour me will I honour, ſaith the Lord. <hi>Pſ. 91.14.</hi> I will ſet him on him, becauſe he hath knowne my name. <hi>Pſal. 112.9.</hi> His horne ſhall bee exalted with honour. <hi>Iohn 12.26.</hi> If any man ſerve me, him will my Father honour. <hi>Prov. 4.7, 8, 9.</hi> Get wiſdome, exalt her, and Shee ſhall promote thee, Shee ſhall bring thee to honour when thou doſt em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace her; Shee ſhall give to thine head an ornament of grace, a crowne of glory ſhall Shee deliver to thee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen the world counts thee as the off-ſcouring of the world, vile, nought-worth: apply,</hi> He ſhall be Gods chiefe treaſure above all people. <hi>Doth the world debaſe thee? apply,</hi> The Lord will exalt thee. The Father will honour him.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="83" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="126" facs="tcp:22966:80"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXXIII. LEGACY.</hi> When thou art in want for ſoule or body.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou art in any want for ſoule or body, apply, Pſalme 34.9.10.</hi> There is no want to them that feare him. The young Lions doe lack and ſuffer hunger, but they that ſeek the Lord ſhall not want any good thing. <hi>Pſalme 84.11.</hi> No good thing will hee withhold from them that walke uprightly. <hi>Mat. 6.33.</hi> Seek yee firſt the Kingdome of God and his righteouſneſſe, and all theſe things ſhall be added unto you. <hi>Art thou trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled with diſtracting cares for out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward things? apply,</hi> Seek the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of Heaven and his righteouſneſse,
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:22966:80"/>and all other things ſhall bee caſt upon you. <hi>Feareſt thou that thou ſhalt bee overpreſſed with want? apply,</hi> Thoſe that ſeek the Lord, ſhall want no good thing. No good thing will bee withhold from them that walke uprightly.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="84" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXXIV. LEGACY.</hi> In liberall giveing.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN liberall giving apply theſe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, Prov. 11.25.</hi> The liberall ſoule ſhall be made fat, and hee that watreth ſhall be watred alſo himſelfe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prov. 19.17.</hi> Hee that hath pitty on the poore, lendeth to the Lord: and that which he hath given will hee pay him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Matth. 6.4.</hi> Give in ſecret, and thy Father himſelfe ſhall reward thee open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly.
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:22966:81"/>
                        <hi>2. Cor. 9.6.10.11.</hi> He which ſoweth bountifully ſhall reape bountifully. He that ministreth ſeed to the ſewer, doth miniſter bread for-your food, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply your ſeed ſowne, and increaſe the fruits of your righteouſneſse, being en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riched in every thing to all bountiful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 58.10.11.</hi> If thou draw out thy ſoule to the hungry, and ſatisfy the af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flicted ſoule: then ſhall thy light riſe in obſcurity, and thy darkneſſe bee as the noone day.</p>
                     <p>And the Lord ſhall guide thee continu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally, and ſatisfy thy ſoule in drought, and make fat thy bones, and thou ſhalt be like a watred garden, and like a ſpring of waters, whoſe waters faile not.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou giveſt to the people of God, and entreateſt them kindly, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Matth. 10, 41.42.</hi> He that receiv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a Prophet in the name of a Prophet, ſhall receive a Prophets reward: and he
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:22966:81"/>that receiveth arighteous man, in the name of a righteous man, ſhall receive a righteous mans reward. And whoſoever ſhall give to drinke unto one of theſe li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle ones a cup of cold water onely in the name of a Diſciple, verily I ſay unto you, he ſhall in no wiſe looſe hiw reward.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="85" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXXV. LEGACY.</hi> If ſickneſſe be among us.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF ſickneſſe be amongſt us, apply, Exod. 23.52.</hi> I will take ſickneſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from the midſt of thee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſalme 43.3.</hi> The Lord will streng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then him upon the bed of languiſhing: 'thou wilt make all his bed in his ſick neſse.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Deut. 7.15.</hi> And the Lord will take away from thee all ſickneſse, and will
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:22966:82"/>put none of the evill diſeaſes of Aegypt upon thee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>If the plague bee among us, apply, Pſalme 91.3.6.7.</hi> Surely hee ſhall deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver thee from the noyſome peſtilence. Thou ſhalt not be afraid of the peſtilence that walketh in darkneſse, nor for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction that waſteth at noone day, A thouſand ſhall fall at thy ſide, and tenne thouſand at thy right hand: but it ſhall not come nigh theee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Art thou ſick? apply,</hi> The Lord wil ſtrengthen him upn the bed of ſorrow: thou wilt make all his bed in his ſick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Art thou there where the ſick are? ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> I will take away all ſickneſſe from the midſt of thee.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Feareſt thou the peſtilence? apply,</hi> I will deliver thee from the noyſome pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stilence.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="86" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="131" facs="tcp:22966:82"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXXVI. LEGACY.</hi> If thou feareſt death.</head>
                     <p>IF thou feareſt death, apply, Iſai. 57.2. <hi>He ſhall enter into peace, they ſhall reſt in their beds.</hi> None feares to goe to bed, when they know they ſhall reſt being weary. This reſting is more ſure and laſting for ever. Rom. 8.11. <hi>He that raiſed up Chriſt from the dead, ſhall quicken our mortall bodies.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore wee muſt not thinke of it but as a better life given by the ſpirit of God.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="87" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="132" facs="tcp:22966:83"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXXVII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou fearest untimely death.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou feareſt untimely death, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Iob. 5.26.</hi> Thou ſhalt come to thy grave in a full age, like as a ſhock of corne commeth in, in his ſeaſon. <hi>Exo. 23.26.</hi> The number of thy dayes will I fulfill. <hi>Pſal. 91.16.</hi> With long life will I ſatisfy him, and ſhew him my ſalvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. <hi>Pſal. 41.2.</hi> The Lord will preſerve him and keep him alive, and he ſhall be bleſsed upon the earth.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Haſt thou many enemies, and feareſt the loſſe of thy life by them? apply,</hi> the number of thy dayes will I fulfill: <hi>the Lord will preſerve him and keep him alive, therefore man cannot ſhorten it one day.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:22966:83"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Feareſt thou that thou ſhalt either live too long, or dye too ſoone? apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt goe to thy gave in a full age, as a rick of corne commeth in due ſeaſon into the barne.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="88" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXXVIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thon feareſt hurt by any of the creatures.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou feareſt hurt by any of the creatures, apply, Gen. 9.2.</hi> The feare of you and the dread of you ſhall beup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on every beaſt of the earth, and upon e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very fowle of the ayre, upon all that moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth upon the earth, upon all the fiſhes of the ſea, into your hand are they delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, <hi>Iob. 5.23.</hi> Thou ſhalt be in league with the stones of the field: and the beaſt of the field ſhall be at peace with thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="89" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="134" facs="tcp:22966:84"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE LXXXIX. LEGACY.</hi> When thou haſt a troubled heart?</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thine heart is troubled either for ſoule or body, apply, Phil. 4.7.</hi> The peace of God which paſſeth all underſtanding, ſhall keep your hearts and minds. <hi>Pſal. 29.11.</hi> The Lord will bleſſe his people with peace.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Is thine heart troubled with many temptations of Satan, or with feares of ſinne and miſery? apply,</hi> The peace of God ſhall preſerve your hearts. <hi>Haſt thou many troubles outwardly? ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> The Lord ſhall bleſſe his people with peace.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="90" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="135" facs="tcp:22966:84"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XC. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wouldſt have thy purpoſe to proſper.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou wouldſt have thy purpoſes to proſper, apply, Iob. 22.28.</hi> Thou ſhalt alſo decree a thing, and it ſhall be eſtabliſhed unto thee: and the light ſhall ſhine upon thy wayes.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 1.3.</hi> Whatſoever he doth ſhall proſper. <hi>Pſal. 37.5.</hi> Commit thy way un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the Lord: truſt alſo in him, and he ſhall bring it to paſse.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou often purpoſeſt to doe good both for thy ſoule and body, and yet findeſt thy purpoſes broken, apply,</hi> Thou ſhal decree a thing, and the Lord ſhall ſtabliſh it unto thee. He ſhall bring it to paſse. <hi>When thou art in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="136" facs="tcp:22966:85"/>of any thing, apply,</hi> Whatſoever he doth ſhall proſper.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="91" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XCI. LEGACY.</hi> When thou art called to a great worke.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou art called to a great work, wherein thou ſhalt have great oppoſition, apply, Deut. 31.8.</hi> The Lord he it is that doty goe before thee, he will be with thee, he will not faile thee, neither for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake thee: feare not, neither be diſmayed, <hi>2. Chro. 16.9.</hi> The Lord will ſhew him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe ſtrong in the behalfe of them whoſe heart is perfect towards him: <hi>Pſal. 91.11, 12, 13.</hi> Hee ſhall give his Angels charge over thee, to keep thee in all thy wayes: They ſhall beare thee up in their
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:22966:85"/>hands, leaſt thou daſh thy foot againſt a ſtone. Thou ſhalt tread upon the Lyon and Adder: the young Lyon and Dragon ſhalt thou trample under feet.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>It matters not what bee that lets op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe us, when the Lord goes before us, hee will eaſily beat them downe: nor what ſtrength reſiſts ſuch, as hee hath promiſed to ſhew his ſtrength for: nor how many bee our dangers, when his Angels have charge over us to keep us. Therefore goe on in the worke, and feare not the iſſue, being ſtrengthened by the promiſes of him, that never faileth his.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="92" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="138" facs="tcp:22966:86"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XCII. LEGACY.</hi> In times of danger.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IN the time of danger, apply, 1. Sam. 2.9.</hi> The Lord will keep the feet of his Saints. <hi>Prov. 1.33.</hi> Who ſo harkeneth unto me ſhall dwell ſaſely, and ſhall bee quiet from feare of evill. <hi>Iob. 11.18.19</hi> Thou ſhalt be ſeeure, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is hope, yea thou ſhalt digge about thee, and thou ſhalt take thy reſt in ſafety, alſo thou ſhalt lye down, and none ſhall make the afraid. <hi>Pſal. 125.1, 2.</hi> They which trust in the Lord, ſhall be as mount Sion which cannot bee re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moved, but abideth for ever. As the mountaines are round about <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> ſo the Lord is round about his people from henceforth, even for ever.</p>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:22966:86"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 121.3, 4, 5.</hi> He will not ſuffer thy foot to be moved: hee that keepeth thee will not ſlumber. Behold, he that keepeth <hi>Iſrael</hi> will neither ſlumber nor ſleep. The Lord is thy keeper, the Lord is thy ſhade upon thy right hand. <hi>Seeing the Lord is our keeper, wee need not feare the danger.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="93" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XCIII. LEGACY.</hi> When thou art in great trouble <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou art in great trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, apply, Iſai. 43.2.</hi> When thou paſsest through the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters I will be with thee, and through the Rivers, they ſhall not overflow thee: when thou walkeſt through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt, neither ſhall the flame
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:22966:87"/>kindle upon thee. <hi>verſ. 20.</hi> I will give waters in the wilderneſſe, and Rivers in the deſart, to give drinke to my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, my choſen. <hi>Pſal. 32.6, 7.</hi> Surely in the floods of great waters they ſhall not come nigh unto him. Thou art my hiding place, thou ſhalt preſerve me from trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; thou ſhalt compaſse me about with ſongs of deliverance.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou ſeeſt thy felſe compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with many troubles, and beginneſt to feare, apply,</hi> I will be with thee, they ſhall not overflow thee. <hi>In the fire of affliction, thou ſhalt not onely not bee burnt, but the flame ſhall not kindle upon thee, the greateſt trouble ſhall doe thee the leaſt harme, for God be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with thee, will bring thee out, as he did</hi> Iſrael <hi>through the ſea, and the three children out of the fire, with not ſo much as the ſavour of fire about them: ſo ſhall not ſo much as the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour of evill bee upon his, but hee
<pb n="141" facs="tcp:22966:87"/>will compaſſe them about with ſongs of deliverance.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="94" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XCIV. LEGACY.</hi> When thou ſeemeſt to be forgot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in affliction.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou ſeemeſt to be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotten in affliction, apply, Pſal. 9.9.18.</hi> The Lord alſo will be a reſnge for the oppreſſed: a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge in times of trouble. For the needy ſhall not alway be forgotten: the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctation of the poore ſhall not periſh for ever.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 48.50.</hi> Can a woman forget her ſucking child, that ſhe ſhould not have compasſion on the ſonne of her wombe? yea, they may forget, yet will not I for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thee. <hi>Pſal. 103.9.</hi> He will not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies
<pb n="142" facs="tcp:22966:88"/>chide, neither will he keep his an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger for ever. <hi>Lam. 3.31, 32.</hi> The Lord will not caſt off for ever. But though he cauſe griefe, yet will he have compasſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, according to the multitude of his mercies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="95" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XCV. LEGACY.</hi> When thou feareſt to dye in miſery.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou feareſt thou ſhalt end thy dayes in miſery, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Iob. 36.11.</hi> They ſhall ſpend their dayes in proſperity, and their yeares in pleaſures.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="96" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="143" facs="tcp:22966:88"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XCVI. LEGACY.</hi> When thy ſorrowes grow great.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thy ſorrowes grow great, apply, Iob. 11.16.</hi> Thou ſhalt forget thy miſery, and remember it as waters that paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way. <hi>Iob. 8.20.21.</hi> Behold, God will not caſt away a perfect man, till he fill thy mouth with laughing, and thy lips with rejoycing, <hi>Pſal. 27.14.</hi> Be of good courage, and hee ſhall ſtrengthen thy heart, <hi>Pſal. 112.4.</hi> Vnto the upright there ariſeth light in the darkneſſe, <hi>Pſal. 126.5.6.</hi> They that ſow in teares ſhall reape in joy. He that goeth forth and weepeth, bearing precious ſeed, ſhall doubtleſse come againe with rejoycing, bringing his ſheaves with him.</p>
                     <pb n="144" facs="tcp:22966:89"/>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Prov. 10.28.</hi> The hope of the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous ſhall be gladneſſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Matth. 5.4.</hi> Bleſſed are they that mourne, for they ſhall be comforted.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iohn 16.62.</hi> Yee now have ſorrow: but I will ſee you again, and your hearts ſhall rejoyce, and your joy no man taketh from you.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Hath ſorrow taken deep root in thy ſoule, that thou feareſt thou ſhalt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver find hearty joy? apply,</hi> Hee ſhall comfort thine heart. <hi>Is ſuch a croſſe upon thee, that thou feareſt thou ſhalt never forget it? apply,</hi> Thou ſhalt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thy miſery, as waters that paſſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="97" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="145" facs="tcp:22966:89"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XCVII. LEGACY.</hi> When thou knoweſt no way out of miſery for ſoule or body.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thou art in ſuch an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, as thou knoweſt no way out of miſery, either for ſoule or body, or both, apply, Ier. 33.3.</hi> Call unto me, and I will anſwer thee, and ſhew thee great and mighty things which thou knoweſt not.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="98" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="146" facs="tcp:22966:90"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XCVIII. LEGACY.</hi> If thou wouldſt have delive<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance out of trouble.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou wouldſt have deliverance out of trouble apply, Pſal. 149.4.</hi> He will beautifie the meek with ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation: <hi>or, Hee will make the meek glorious by deliverance</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Pſal. 34.17.19.</hi> The righteous cry, and the Lord heareth: and delivereth them out of all their troubles. Many are the afflictions of the righteous: but the Lord delivereth him out of them all. <hi>Iob. 5.17, 18, 19.</hi> Happy is the man whom God correcteth, for hee maketh ſore, and bindeth up: he woundeth, and his hands make whole. he ſhall deliver thee in ſixe troubles, in ſeaven there
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:22966:90"/>ſhall no evill touch thee. <hi>Pſal. 50.15.</hi> Call upon me in the day of trouble: I will deliver thee, and thou ſhalt glorify me.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>When thou art in many troubles, and feareſt thou ſhalt never get out of all, apply,</hi> The Lord will deliver the out of all. <hi>If the Lord hath delivered thee once or twice, and thou feareſt he will not continue ſo ſtill, as often as thou falleſt into troubles, apply,</hi> He ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liver thee in ſixe troubles, and the ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venth it ſhall not touch thee.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="99" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE XCIX. LEGACY.</hi> If thine enemies prevaile.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>WHen thine enemies prevaile, apply, Pſal. 125.3.</hi> Theroà of the wicked ſhall not rest
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:22966:91"/>upon the lot of the righteous: least the righteous put forth their hands unto in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iquity: <hi>Pſal. 18.3.</hi> I will call upon the Lord: ſo ſhall I be ſaved from mine ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies. <hi>1. Sam. 2.10.</hi> The adverſaries of the Lord ſhall bee broken to pieces: the eyes of the wicked ſhall faile, their re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuge ſhall periſh, their hope ſhall bee ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row of mind. <hi>Iob. 11.20. Deut. 28.7.</hi> The Lord ſhall cauſe thine enemies that riſe up againſt thee, to be ſmitten before thy face.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Seeſt thou many to riſe up to trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble thee? apply,</hi> thine enemies that riſe againſt-thee, ſhall fall before thy face. <hi>Hope they to prevaile againſt thee? ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply,</hi> their hope ſhall be ſorrow of mind: <hi>Have they great meanes to cauſe them to proſper? apply,</hi> their refuge ſhall periſh. <hi>Have they long oppreſſed thee? apply,</hi> the rod of the wicked ſhall not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes rest upon the lot of the righteous. <hi>Seeſt thou no meanes to get from
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:22966:91"/>them? ſay with the Prophet David</hi> I will call upon the Lord, ſo ſhall I be ſafe from mine enemies.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="100" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE C. LEGACY.</hi> That thou maiſt be delivered, and thine enemies afflicted</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THat thou maiſt bee delivered, and thine enemies afflicted in thy ſtead, apply, Deut. 30.7.</hi> The Lord thy God will put all theſe cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes upon thine enemies, and on them that hate thee, which per ſecute thee. <hi>Prov. 21.18.</hi> The wicked ſhall be a ranſome for the righteous, and the tranſgreſsour for the upright.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="101" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="150" facs="tcp:22966:92"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE CI. LEGACY.</hi> Jf thou wouldst have thine enemies deſtroyed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF thou wouldſt have thine enemies deſtroyed, apply, Iob. 8.22.</hi> They that hate thee ſhall be cloat hed with ſhame, and the dwelling place of the wicked ſhall come to nought.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Iſai. 41.11.13.15.</hi> Behold all they which-were incenſed againſt thee ſhall be aſhamed and confounded, they ſhall be as nothing, and they that ſtrive with thee ſhall periſh: for I the Lord thy God will hold thy right hand, ſaying unto thee, Feare not, I will help thee. Thou ſhalt threſh the mountaines and beat them ſmall, and ſhalt make the hils as chaffe, <hi>by which mountaines and hills,
<pb n="151" facs="tcp:22966:92"/>is meant the greateſt enemies. 1. Sam. 2.30.</hi> They that deſpiſe me ſhal be light<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly eſteemed. <hi>Theſe promiſes are to be applyed by us, as they are the enemies of God and his Goſpell, and ours for his ſake.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="102" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE CII. LEGACY.</hi> Jf the wicked plot against thee.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>IF the wicked plot againſt thee, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Pſal. 37.12.</hi> The wicked plot a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the just; their ſword ſhall en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter into their owne heart, their bow ſhall be broken. The Lord ſhall laugh at him. <hi>Iſai. 54.15.</hi> The enemies ſhall ſurely ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther themſelves together againſt thee, but not by me; whoſoever ſhall gather themſelves together againſt thee ſhall fall.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="103" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="152" facs="tcp:22966:93"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE CIII. LEGACY.</hi> In the troubles of the Church.</head>
                     <p>IN the troubles of the Church, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, Pſal. 128.6. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſee peace upon</hi> Iſrael, verſ. 5. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſee the good of</hi> Ieruſalem <hi>all the dayes of thy life.</hi> Ier. 31.12. <hi>Thou ſhalt come and ſing in the height of</hi> Sion: when thou haſt applyed the promiſes, and uſed all the meanes, and yet findeſt not thy ſelfe filled with God, as thou deſireſt, then comfort thy ſelfe with this, <hi>Yet a little while, and when thou awakeſt, thou ſhalt bee ſatisfied with his Image.</hi> Pſal. 17.15.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="104" type="legacy">
                     <pb n="153" facs="tcp:22966:93"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE CIV. LEGACY.</hi> For the fall of Antichriſt.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>BEcauſe the time draweth neere of the fall of Antichriſt, we muſt ſtirre up our ſelves to haſten the Lord by carneſt prayers, and for the ſtrengthening of our faith, apply theſe promiſes, Rev. 17.16.</hi> And the tenne hornes which thouſaweſt upon the Beaſt, theſe ſhall hate the Whore, and ſhall make her deſolate and naked and ſhall eat her fleſh, and ſhall burn her with fire, <hi>Rev. 18.8.21.</hi> Therefore ſhall her plagues come in in one day, death and mourning, and famine, and ſhe ſhall be utterly burnt with fire, for strong is the Lord God who judgeth her. And a might<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Angell tooke up a great stone, like a
<pb n="154" facs="tcp:22966:94"/>great Milſtone, and caſt it into the ſea, ſaying, Thus with violence ſhall that great Citty <hi>Babylon</hi> be throwne down, and ſhall be found no more at all. <hi>Even ſo come Lord Ieſus, and haſten this happy day.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="105" type="legacy">
                     <head>
                        <hi>THE CV. LEGACY.</hi> For the calling of the Iewes.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>SEeing the Lord hath promiſed many glorious things to the Iewes with much grace and peace, both to the Iewes and Gentiles at their converſion; when the renne tribes ſhall bee reunited to the two, which hever yet was, let us never give him reſt till hee ſet up</hi> Ieruſalem <hi>the praiſe of the world, and for the ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thening of us in prayer, apply, theſe
<pb n="155" facs="tcp:22966:94"/>promiſes: Ezek. 37.21, 22.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord God, Behold, I will take the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> from among the hea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>then, whit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>her they be gone, and will ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther them on every ſide, and bring them into their owne land: and I will make them one nation, in the land upon the mountaines of <hi>Iſrael:</hi> and one King ſhall be King to them all, and they ſhall be no more two Nations, neither ſhall they be divided into two Kingdomes any more at all, <hi>Ier. 3.18.</hi> In thoſe dayes the houſe of <hi>Iudah</hi> ſhall walke with the hovſe of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and they ſhall come together out of the land of the North to the land that I have given for an inheritance unto your fathers: <hi>Iſai. 60.2, 3, 4, 5.15.16.</hi> The Lord ſhall ariſe upon thee, and his glory ſhall be ſeen upon thee. And the Gentiles ſhall come to the light, and Kings to the brightneſſe of thy riſing, thy ſonnes ſhall come from farre, and thy daughters ſhall be nurſed at thy ſide
<pb n="156" facs="tcp:22966:95"/>then thou ſhalt ſee and flow together, and thine heart ſhall feare and be enlarged, becauſe the Sea ſhall be converted unto thee: the forces of the Gentiles ſhall come unto thee. Whereas thou haſt been for ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken and hated, ſo that no man went through thee, I will make thee an eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall excellency, a joy of many generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: Thou ſhalt alſo ſuck the milk of the Gentiles, and ſhalt ſuck the breast of Kings. <hi>Iſai. 62.2, 3.49.</hi> The Gentiles ſhall ſee thy righteouſneſse, and all Kings thy glory, and thou ſhalt be called by a new name, which the mouth of the Lord ſhall name, thou ſhalt alſo be a crown of glory in the band of the Lord, and a roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all diadem in the hand of thy God. <hi>Iſai. 61.4, 5, 6.</hi> They ſhall build the old waſts, they ſhall raiſe up the former deſolati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, they ſhall repayre the wast cities, the deſolations of many generations. And strangers ſhall ſtand and feed your ſtocks, and the ſonnes of the alien ſhall
<pb n="157" facs="tcp:22966:95" rendition="simple:additions"/>by your plowmen, and your vine-dreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſers, but ye ſhall be named the Priests of the Lord: men ſhall call you the mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sters of our God, ye ſhall eat the riches of the Gentiles, and in their glory ſhall you boaſt your ſelves. <hi>Iſai. 48.22, 23.</hi> Thus ſaith the Lord: Behold, I will lift up my hand to the Gentiles, and ſet up my standard to the people, and they ſhall bring thy ſonnes in their armes, and thy daughters ſhall be carried upon their ſhoulders, and Kings ſhall be thy nurſing Fathers, and their Queenes thy nurſing Mothers, they ſhall bow downe to thee with their face toward the earth, and lick vp the duſt of thy feet.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:96" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <head>A Poſt-ſcript ſent from the Authour.</head>
                  <p>THeſe promiſes I have obſerved: ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more there be of moſt excellent uſe, but becauſe they need opening for the underſtanding of them, I would not ſet them downe, leaſt through the ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowneſſe of my underſtanding I ſhould wrong the precious promiſes: but I picked out the moſt plaine, and thoſe that I found of continuall uſe for ſoule and body, which I have found much good by, for the promiſes are our Legacies bequeathed to us in the will of our Father, and wee are to claime them, as wee ſtand in need of any of them: and ſurely that God which would not have children wronged in that which is bequeathed to them in the will of their Fathers, much leſſe will hee withhold that which his Sonne hath bequeathed to us in his laſt will, which hee ſealeed with his blood, Therefore let us ſue for them, for he ſaith, hee will bee ſought to performe
<pb facs="tcp:22966:96"/>them to us. And when thou applyeſt any promiſe, ſeeke unto the condition, and labour to keep it, and doubt not of the performance of what is promiſed, for he is both able and faithfull that hath promiſed.</p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:97"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:97"/>
                  <p>AN EPITOME OF PROMISES FOR THE <hi>SAINTS SVPPORT</hi> IN TIME OF TROVBLE.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>The ſixth Edition.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>PSAL. 119.140.</hi>
                     </bibl> Thy Word is very pure, therefore thy ſervants love it.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>OXFORD,</hi> Printed by LEON. LICHFIELD, for <hi>Samuel Enderby.</hi> An. Dom. 1640.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="text">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:98"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:22966:98"/>
                  <head>AN EPITOME OF PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MISES FOR THE SAINTS SVPPORT IN TIME OF TROVBLE.</head>
                  <head type="sub">Promiſes.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="promise">
                     <head>I.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>THat God hath freely loved his Elect in Chriſt Ieſus.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will be gracious, to whom I will be gracious: and I will ſhew mercy, on whom I will ſhew mercy. <hi>Exod. 33.19.</hi>
                        <pb n="2" facs="tcp:22966:99"/>I even I am he that blotteth out thy tranſgreſsion: for mine owne ſake. <hi>Eſa. 43.25.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I have blotted out as a thick Cloud thy tranſgreſsions. <hi>Eſa. 44.22.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will heale their back-ſlidings: I will love them freely. <hi>Hoſea 14.4.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="promise">
                     <head>II. That GOD hath given Chriſt to death for his Elect.</head>
                     <p>I will put emnity betweene thee and the woman: it ſhall bruiſe thy head, and thou ſhalt bruiſe his heele. <hi>Gen. 3.15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>But he was wounded for our tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſsion. <hi>Eſa. 53.5.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When he ſhall make his ſoule an offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring for ſin. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hewas numbred with the tranſgreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſors,
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:22966:99"/>and bare the ſinnes of many. <hi>12.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Seaventy weeks are determined upon the people to finiſh the tranſgreſsions, and to make an end of ſin. <hi>Dan. 9.24.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="3" type="promise">
                     <head>III. That wee are freely juſtified by Ieſus Chriſt.</head>
                     <p>So by the obedience of one, many ſhall be made righteous: <hi>Rom. 5.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And are juſtified freely by his grace: through the redemption that is in Chriſt Ieſus. <hi>Rom. 3.24.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>By his knowledge ſhall my righteous ſervant juſtify many. <hi>Eſa. 53.11.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="promise">
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:22966:100"/>
                     <head>IV. That GOD hath made a Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with his Children to be their GOD.</head>
                     <p>I will establiſh my Covenant between me and thee, and thy ſeed after thee in their generations for an everlaſting Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant, to be a God unto thee and to thy ſeed after thee. <hi>Gen. 17.7.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will walk among you, and will be yoür God, and ye ſhall be my people. <hi>Lev. 26.26.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>With great and eternall mercies will I gather thee. <hi>Eſa. 54.7.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will be their God, and they ſhall be my people. <hi>Ier. 31.33.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will ſay to them; Thou art my peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and they ſhall ſay, thou art my God. <hi>Hoſea 2.23.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="promise">
                     <pb n="5" facs="tcp:22966:100"/>
                     <head>V. That GOD will call his Children to the knowledge of his Truth.</head>
                     <p>The meek will he teach his wayes. <hi>Pſal. 25.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will inſtruct thee, and teach thee in all the way that thou ſhalt goe. <hi>Pſal. 32.8.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All thy Children ſhall be taught of the Lord. <hi>Eſa. 54.13.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For they ſhall all know me from the least of them to the greateſt, ſaith the Lord. <hi>Ier. 31.34.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I am the Lordthy God which teacheth thee to profit, and leadeth thee by the way that thou ſhouldſt goe. <hi>Eſa. 48.17.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="6" type="promise">
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:22966:101"/>
                     <head>VI. That GOD will give his Spirit unto his children.</head>
                     <p>I will power out my ſpirit upon you. <hi>Prov. 1.23.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will powre water upon him that is thirſty. <hi>Eſa. 44.3.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will put my ſpirit within you. <hi>Ezek. 36.27.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will powre out my ſpirit upon all fleſh. <hi>Ioel 2.28</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will powre upon the houſe of <hi>David</hi> the ſpirit. <hi>Zach. 12.10.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will pray unto the Father, and he ſhall give you even the ſpirit of Truth. <hi>Iohn 14.16, 17.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="7" type="promise">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:22966:101"/>
                     <head>VII. That GOD will cauſe his Children to truſt in him by faith.</head>
                     <p>Many ſhall ſee it and feare, and ſhall truſt in the Lord. <hi>Pſal. 40.3.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Vnder his wings ſhalt thou truſt. <hi>91.4.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>On my armes ſhall they truſt. <hi>Eſa. 51.1.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The juſt ſhall live by his faith. <hi>Hab. 2.4.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>They ſhall trust in the name of the Lord. <hi>Zeph. 3.12.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In his Name ſhall the Gentiles trust. <hi>Matth. 12.21.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="8" type="promise">
                     <pb n="8" facs="tcp:22966:102"/>
                     <head>VIII. That God will give his Children an humble and broken heart.</head>
                     <p>I will take the ſtony heart out of their fleſh, and I will give them a heart of fleſh. <hi>Ezek. 11.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will powre on them the ſpirit of ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plication, and they ſhall mourne for him as one mourneth for his Onely Sonne. <hi>Zach. 12.10.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Every mountaine and hill ſhall bee brought low. <hi>Luk. 3.5.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lord thy God will circumciſe thy heart. <hi>Deut. 30.6.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="9" type="promise">
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:22966:102"/>
                     <head>X. That Gods Children ſhall have pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to mortify and overcome ſin.</head>
                     <p>For ſin ſhall not have dominion over you, for ye are not under the Law, but under Grace. <hi>Rom. 6.12.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will ſprinkle clean water upon you, and ye ſhall be cleanſed from all your fil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thineſſe. <hi>Ezek. 36.25.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He will ſubdue our iniquities. <hi>Micah. 7.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Every branch that beareth fruit he purgeth it.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="10" type="promise">
                     <head>X. That the Children of God ſhall live a holy and ſanctified life.</head>
                     <p>He ſhall be like a tree that bringeth
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:22966:103"/>forth fruit in his ſeaſon. <hi>Pſal. 1.3.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will put my Law into their inward parts. <hi>Ier. 31.33.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The ſound thereof ſhall be as the wine of <hi>Lebanon. Hoſea</hi> 14.7.</p>
                     <p>For their ſakes ſanctify I my ſelfe, that they may be ſanctified through the Truth. <hi>Iohn 17.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>In holineſse and righteouſneſſe all the days of our lives. <hi>Luke 1.75.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lord of peace ſanctify you throughout. <hi>1. Theſ. 5.23.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Faithfull is he that hath promiſed you. <hi>verſ. 24.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="11" type="promise">
                     <head>XI They that love God.</head>
                     <p>I will circumciſe thy heart, and the heart of thy ſeed, to love the Lord thy God with all thy heart, and with all thy
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:22966:103"/>ſoule, that thou maiſt live. <hi>Deut. 30.6.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="12" type="promise">
                     <head>XII. That GOD will give his Children hearts to delight in all his holy Ordinances.</head>
                     <p>With gladne sand rejoycing ſhall they be brought: They ſhall enter into the Kings Pallace. <hi>Pſal. 45.15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore with joy ſhall they draw waters out of the Wells of Salvation. <hi>Eſa. 12.3.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And in this mountaine ſhall the Lord of Hoſts make unto all people a feaſt of fat things. <hi>25.26.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Even them will I bring to my holy mountaine, and make them joy full in my houſe of Prayer. <hi>56.7.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Ye ſhall be borne upon her ſides, and be dandled upon her knees. <hi>66.12.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:22966:104"/>
                     <p>So will I comfort you, and ye ſhall be comforted. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And when yee ſee this, your hearts ſhall be comforted. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The feaſt of the tenth moneth ſhall be unto the houſe of <hi>ludah,</hi> joy and glad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſse, and chearefull Feaſts. <hi>Zach. 8.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="13" type="promise">
                     <head>XIII That God will give his Children hearts to feare and ſerve him.</head>
                     <p>They ſhall ſanctify my name, and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctify the holineſſe of <hi>Iacob,</hi> and ſhall feare the God of <hi>Iſrael. Eſa.</hi> 29.23.</p>
                     <p>They ſhall ſerve the Lord their God, and <hi>David</hi> their King. <hi>Ier. 30.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will give them one heart and one way, that they may feare me for ever. <hi>Ier. 32.39.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>That wee being delivered out of the
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:22966:104"/>hands of our enemies, might ſerve him without feare. <hi>Luke 1.74.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="14" type="promise">
                     <head>XIV. That God will give his Children hearts to ſeek him by prayer.</head>
                     <p>He ſhall call upon me, and I will heare him. <hi>Pſal. 91.15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then ſhall yee call upon me, and yee ſhall pray unto me, and I will heare you. <hi>Ier. 29.12.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And yee ſhall ſeek me and find me: ſearch for me with all your hearts. <hi>13.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will powre upon the houſe of <hi>David,</hi> and upon the Inhabitants of <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> the ſpirit of Grace and of Supplication. <hi>Zach. 12.10.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="15" type="promise">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:22966:105"/>
                     <head>XV. That God will heare the Prayers of his Children.</head>
                     <p>Call upon me in the day of Trouble, and I will deliver thee. <hi>Pſal. 50.15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He ſhall call upon me, and I will an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer him. <hi>91.15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He will heare their cry, and will ſave them. <hi>145.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then ſhalt thou call, and the Lord ſhall anſwer. <hi>Eſa. 58.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Before they call, I will anſwer, and while they are ſpeaking I will heare. 65.24.</p>
                     <p>He ſhall ſeek me and ſhall find me, when you ſhall ſeek I will bee found of you. <hi>Ier. 29.13, 14.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Yee ſhall aske what yee will, and it ſhall be done unto you. <hi>Iohn 15.7.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="15" facs="tcp:22966:105"/>
                     <p>Aske and it ſhall bee given your ſeek and ye ſhall find. <hi>Matth. 7.7.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>What ſoever ye ſhall aske in prayer, believing ye ſhall receive. <hi>Mat. 21.22.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="16" type="promise">
                     <head>XVI. That we may perſevere in grace.</head>
                     <p>They ſhall bring forth fruit in their old age. <hi>Pſalm. 21.14.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>His leafe ſhall not wither. <hi>1.2.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lord <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> guide thee continual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and ſatisfy thy ſoule in drought; and make fat thy bones; and thou ſhalt be like a watred Garden, and like a ſpring whoſe waters faile not. <hi>Eſa. 58.11.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="17" type="promise">
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:22966:106"/>
                     <head>XVII. That God will give unto his Children the good things of this life.</head>
                     <p>But the meek ſhall inherit the earth: and ſhall delight themſelves in the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundance of pence. <hi>Pſal. 37.11.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There is no want to them that ſeek him. <hi>Pſal. 34.11.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>They that ſeek the Lord ſhall not want any good thing. <hi>1</hi> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 span">
                           <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </p>
                     <p>No good thing ſhall he withhold from them that walk uprightly. <hi>Pſal. 84.11.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="18" type="promise">
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:22966:106"/>
                     <head>XVIII. That God will guide his Children by his ſpeciall providence in all their wayes.</head>
                     <p>I will not leave thee nor for ſake thee. <hi>Heb. 13.15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then ſhalt thou walk in thy way ſafe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and thy foot ſhall not ſtumble. <hi>Prov. 3.23.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For the Lord ſhall be thy Confidence. <hi>26.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He ſhall give his Angels charge over thee to keep thee in all thy wayes. <hi>Pſal. 91.11.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lord ſhall preſerve thy going out and thy comming in. <hi>121.8.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And even to your old age I am he, and even to hoare-haires will I carry you. <hi>Eſa. 46.4.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="19" type="promise">
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:22966:107"/>
                     <head>XIX. That God will bleſſe thoſe which are diligent in their Calling.</head>
                     <p>The Lord will command the bleſſing upon thee in all thou ſetteſt thy hand un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to. <hi>Deut. 28.8.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt eat the labour of thy hand: happy ſhalt thou be, and it ſhall bee well with thee. <hi>Pſal. 128.2.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The hand of the diligent maketh rich. <hi>Prov. 10.4.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He that tilleth his land, ſhall be ſatis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied with bread. <hi>12.11.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="20" type="promise">
                     <head>XX.</head>
                     <p>That God will bleſſe thoſe that keep his Sabbaths.</p>
                     <p>Bleſſed is the man that keepeth the
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:22966:107"/>Sabbath from polluting it. <hi>Eſa. 56.2.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>If thou turne away thy foot from the Sabbath, from doing thy pleaſure on my holy day: and call the Sabbath a delight: <hi>58.13.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then ſhall <hi>&amp;c. 14.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then this City ſhall remaine for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver. <hi>Ier. 17.24.25.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="21" type="promise">
                     <head>XXI. That God will reward thoſe that are fruitfull in good works.</head>
                     <p>He hath given to the poore: his righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſse endureth for ever. <hi>Pſ. 112.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The liberall ſoule ſhall be made fat: and he that watereth, ſhall bee watered alſo himſelf. <hi>Prov. 11.25.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Honour the Lord with thy ſub ſtance, and with the first fruits of all thine in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe. <hi>Prov. 3.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:22966:108"/>
                     <p>So ſhall thy barnes be filled with plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty: and thy preſſes ſhall burst with new wine. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He that hath a bountifull eye ſhall be bleſſed: for bee giveth of his bread to the poore. <hi>Prov. 22.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He that giveth to the poore ſhall not lack: but hee that hideth his eye, ſhall have many a curſe. <hi>Prov. 28.27.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Caſt thy bread upon the waters: For thou ſhalt find it after many dayes. <hi>Eccleſ. 11.1.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Bleſsed are the mercifull, for they ſhall obtaine mercy. <hi>Mat. 5.7.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whoſoever ſhall give to drinke unto one of theſe litle ones a cup of cold wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter: he ſhall in no wiſe looſe his reward. <hi>Matth. 10.42.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then ſhall the King ſay to them on his right hand. Come yee bleſſed of my Father, inherit the Kingdome prepared for you from the foundation of the world. <hi>25.34.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="22" type="promise">
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:22966:108"/>
                     <head>XXII. That we ſhall receive good by he ſociety of the faithfull.</head>
                     <p>He that walketh with wiſe men ſhall be wiſe. <hi>Prov. 13.20.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then they that feared the Lord, ſpake of ten one to another: and the Lord hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kened and heard it. And a book of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>membrance was written before him, for them that feared the Lord and thought upon his Name. <hi>Malach. 3.16.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And they ſhall bee mine ſaith the Lord God of Hoſts, in that day when I make up my Iewels, and I will ſpare them, as a man ſpareth his owne ſonne that ſerveth him. <hi>17.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For where two or three bee gathered together in my name: there am I in the midſt of them. <hi>Matth. 18.20.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="23" type="promise">
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:22966:109"/>
                     <head>XXIII. That God will keep afflictions from his Children as it may bee for their good.</head>
                     <p>The Lord ſhall preſerve thee from all evill. <hi>Pſal. 121.7.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lord ſhall preſerve thy going out and thy comming in from this time forth and for evermore.</p>
                     <p>He ſhall cover thee with his feathers, and under his wings ſhalt thou truſt: his truth ſhall bee thy Shield and Buckler. <hi>Pſal. 91.4.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>There ſhall no evill befall thee: nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhall any plague come neare thy dwelling. <hi>10.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>As the mountaines are about Ieruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem, ſo is the Lord about his people for ever. <hi>Pſal. 125.2.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="24" type="promise">
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:22966:109"/>
                     <head>XXIV. That otherwiſe God will bee with, preſerve and keep his Children in afflictions that they hurt them not.</head>
                     <p>In all their afflictions hee was affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted, and the Angell of his preſence ſaved them: in his love, and in his pitty he re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed them, and he bare them and car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried them all the dayes of old. <hi>Eſa. 63.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>They ſhall not be aſhamed in the evill time, and in the dayes of famine they ſhall be ſatis ſied. <hi>Pſal. 37.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He is their ſtrength in the time of trouble. <hi>39.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The Lord ſhall help and deliver them from the wicked, and ſave them becauſe they truſt in him. <hi>40.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Feare thou not, for I am with the, be
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:22966:110"/>not diſmayed, for I am thy God; I will ſtrengthen thee, yea I will helpe thee, yea I will uphold thee with the right hand of my righteouſneſſe.</p>
                     <p>Feare not thou worme Iacob: I will helpe thee ſaith the Lord God, and thy Redeemer the hold One of Iſrael. <hi>14.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When thou paſseſt through the water I will be with thee: and through the Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers, that they ſhall not over-flow thee. When thon walkest through the fire, thou ſhalt not be burnt: neither ſhall the flames kindle vpon thee. <hi>Eſa. 43.2.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="25" type="promise">
                     <head>XXV. That God will deliver his Children out of afflictions in his due time.</head>
                     <p>He ſhall deliver thee from the ſnare of the fowler, and from the noyſome pesti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence.</p>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:22966:110"/>
                     <p>I will be with him in trouble: I will deliver him and honour him. <hi>15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Many are the troubles of the righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, but the Lord delivers them out of them all. <hi>Pſalm. 34.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Call upon me in the day of trouble, and I will deliver thee. <hi>Pſal. 50.15.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will reſtore health unto thee: I will heale thee of thy wounds ſaith the Lord. <hi>Ier. 30.17.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will deliver thee in that day, and thou ſhalt not fall by the ſword. <hi>Ier. 39.17. Iohn. 3.19.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="26" type="promise">
                     <head>XXVI. That God will ſanctify all afflictions for the good of his people.</head>
                     <p>I will turn my hand upon thee, and purely purge away thy droſſe, and take away all thy tynne. <hi>Eſa. 1.25.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:22966:111"/>
                     <p>By this therefore ſhall the iniquity of <hi>Iacob</hi> be purged, and this is all the fruit to take away his ſinne. <hi>Eſa. 27.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And ſome of them of understanding ſhall fall to try them, and to purge and make them white. <hi>Dan. 11.35.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Many ſhall bee purified and made white and tryed. <hi>Dan. 12.10.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And I will bring the third part through the fire: and I will refine them as ſilver is refined, and will try them as gold is tryed: they ſhall call on my Name, and I will heare them. <hi>Zach. 13.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="27" type="promise">
                     <head>XXVIII. That God in his owne time will ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>due all the enemies of his Church.</head>
                     <p>I will ſubdue all thy enemies. <hi>2. Chr. 17.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I will puniſh the fruit of the ſtout
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:22966:111"/>heart of the King of <hi>Aſſyria:</hi> and the glory of his high lookes. <hi>Eſa. 10.12.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Therefore I will put my hooke in thy noſe, and my bridle in thy lips: and I will turn thee back by the way which thou cameſt. <hi>Eſa. 37.29.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For the armes of the wicked ſhall bee broken. <hi>Pſal. 37.17.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>I am againſt thee O Gog. <hi>Ezek. 39.1.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And I will turn thee back. <hi>2.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And then ſhall that wicked bee revea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, whom the Lord ſhall conſume with the ſpirit of his mouth, and ſhall deſtroy with the brightneſse of his comming. <hi>2. Theſ. 2.8.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And the ten hornes, theſe ſhall hate the whore and ſhall make her deſolate and naked, and ſhall eat her fleſh and burn her with fire. <hi>Rev. 17.16.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> will ſmite thy bow our of thy left hand, and <hi>I</hi> will cauſe thy arrowes to fall out of thy right hand. <hi>Ezek. 39.3.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="28" type="promise">
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:22966:112"/>
                     <head>XXVIII. That the Children of God ſhall dye happily.</head>
                     <p>They ſhall come to the grave in a full age: like as a ſhocke of Corne commeth in his ſeaſon. <hi>Iob. 5.26.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He ſhall goe in peace, they ſhall reſt in their beds: each one walking in his up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rightneſse. <hi>Eſa. 57.2.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Marke the perfect man, and behold the upright: for the end of that man is peace. <hi>Pſal. 37.37.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="29" type="promise">
                     <head>XXIX. That the juſt ſhall bee raiſed unto eternall life.</head>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> will ranſome them from the power
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:22966:112"/>of the grave: <hi>I</hi> will redeem them from death: O death, I will be thy plague: O grave, I will be thy deſtruction. <hi>Hoſ. 13.14.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>And many of them that ſleep in the duſt of the earth ſhall awake to everlaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life, and ſome to ſhame. <hi>Dan. 12.2.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>All that are in the graves ſhall come forth: they that have done good, unto the Reſurrection of life. <hi>Ioh. 5.29.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>I</hi> will raiſe him up at the laſt day. <hi>6.40.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>He that raiſed up the Lord Ieſus, ſhall raiſe us up alſo by Ieſus. <hi>2. Cor. 4.14.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>When Christ who is our life ſhall ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare, then ſhall yee appeare with him in glory. <hi>Coloſ. 3.4.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="30" type="promise">
                     <head>XXX. That God will reward the labours of the righteous in the life to come.</head>
                     <p>Rejoyce and be glad, for great is your
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:22966:113"/>reward in heaven. <hi>Matth. 5.12.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Whoſoever ſhall forſake houſes, or bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, or ſisters, or father, or mother, or wife, or children, or lands for my Names ſake, h ſhal receive a hundred fold more, and ſhall inherit everlaſting life. <hi>19.29.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Come ye bleſſed of my Father: inherit yet the Kingdome prepared for you be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the foundation of the world. <hi>Math. 25.34.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thou ſhalt bee recompenſed at the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the just. <hi>Luk. 14.14.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Hee that overcometh ſhall inherit all things. <hi>Rev. 21.7.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="31" type="promise">
                     <head>XXXI. That God will make good and per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme all that he hath promiſed</head>
                     <p>And <hi>I</hi> will performe the Oath which <hi>I</hi> ſware unto <hi>Abraham</hi> thy Father.
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:22966:113"/>
                        <hi>Gen. 26.3.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Know therefore that the Lord thy God he is God; the faithfull God; which keepeth Covenant and mercy with them that love him. <hi>Deut. 7.9.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Bleſſed be the Lord that hath given rest unto his people; there hath not fay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led one word of all his good promiſes which he promiſed. <hi>1. Kings 8.56.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>My Covenant will I not breake, nor alter the thing that is gone out of my lips. <hi>Pſal. 89.34.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Thus ſaith the Lord, if you can break my Covenant of the day, and my Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant of the night; That there ſhould not be day and night in their ſeaſon, <hi>Ier. 33.20.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Then may alſo my Covenant bee bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken. <hi>21.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>For all the promiſes of God in him are yea, and in him, <hi>Amen. 2. Cor. 1.20.</hi>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:114"/>
                     <p n="1">1. GIve me underſtanding and I ſhall keepe thy Word: yea I will obſerve it with my whole heart. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.34.</p>
                     <p>Deale with thy ſervant ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording thy mercies, and teach me thy Statutes. <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 119.124.</p>
                     <p n="2">2. How ſweet are thy words unto my taſte: yea ſwee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter then honey to my mouth.
<pb facs="tcp:22966:114"/>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.103.</p>
                     <p>What ſhall J render unto the Lord for all his benefits to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards me? <hi>Pſalm.</hi> 116.12.</p>
                     <p n="3">3. Conſider how I love thy precepts, quicken me O Lord, according to thy loving kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.159.</p>
                     <p>With my whole heart have I ſought thee, O let me not wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der from thy Commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.10.</p>
                     <p n="4">4. For ever O Lord, thy Word is ſetled in heaven: thy faithfulneſſe is unto all genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions.
<pb facs="tcp:22966:115"/>
                        <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.19.</p>
                     <p>Plead my cauſe and deliver me, quicken me according to thy Word. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.154.</p>
                     <p n="5">5. Whatſoever the Lord pleaſed, that did hee in heaven and in earth. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 335.6.</p>
                     <p>Make me to underſtand the way of thy precepts, ſo ſhall I talke of thy wondrous works. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 11.27.</p>
                     <p n="6">6. Remember thy Word unto thy ſervant, upon which thou haſt cauſed me to hope. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.49.</p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:115"/>
                     <p>Who is like unto the Lord our God, who dwelleth on high? <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113.5.</p>
                     <p n="7">7. Incline my heart unto thy Teſtimonie, and not unto Covetouſneſſe. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.36.</p>
                     <p>When my ſpirit was over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>whelmed within me, thou kneweſt my paths <hi>Pſal.</hi> 142.3.</p>
                     <p n="8">8. My ſoule is continually in my hand, yet doe J not for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get thy Law, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.109.</p>
                     <p>Stabliſh thy word unto thy ſeruant, who is devoted to thy feare. <hi>Pſal.</hi> 119.38.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div type="postscript">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:116"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:116"/>
                  <head>A POSTSCRIPT, TO ALL TRVE BELEEVERS.</head>
                  <opener>
                     <salute>Gracious Beleevers,</salute>
                  </opener>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">K</seg>Nowing you to be the only heires of thoſe rich and precious promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, which it hath pleaſed our gracious Father freely to give unto his freely beloved Children: I have preſumed without your knowledge, to bequeath unto you a fatherleſſe child brought forth into the world without the pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents knowledge, hoping you will not be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>willing to let it paſſe under your favourable protection, For the ſubject matter of it, it is
<pb facs="tcp:22966:117"/>very beautifull, and of ſuch uſe, as no child of God can paſſe to Heaven without it, and in that regard, it ſhall bee no ſhame unto you whom the Lord hath honoured with the grace of believing, to accept of this ſmall, Treatiſe from one that deſires your prospering in your ſoules and bodies. There is no blemiſh in this that I dedicate unto you, but ſuch as came by the hands of the unskilfull bringer forth of it, which only minded their own good in it. And weighing dayly the beauty of it, and the ſweet refreſhing ſtrength which flowed from it, for the overcomming of thoſe three deadly ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies, the Devill, Sin, and the World, they deſired that Ged would bee pleaſed to move the minds of ſome of his moſt skilfull work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, to put to their hands to frame a more perfect work upon ſo perfect a ſubject, and to give a more comely forme, to this ſo beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full a ſubject, and till then they intended to ſmoother in their boſomes the beauty of this, rather then to bring it forth with the blemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhes of their unskilfulneſſe. But the good that may be gayned by it being unutterable, I hope grace in the hearts of Gods people will cauſe them, like the Bee, to ſuck out the ſweet and
<pb facs="tcp:22966:117"/>nouriſhing vertue of theſe fragrant flowers, that grow here and there in the garden of Gods word, and not with diſcontent to caſt away this pleaſant poſy gathered out of the celeſtiall <hi>Eden</hi> of the ſacred Scriptures, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe an unskilfull hand, and indeed unwor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy, hath bound them up together, not ſo order<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly as might pleaſe the curious eye of man, no nor their owne, neither was it their ayme ſo to doe. J fany gaine any good by it, the gathe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer of theſe ſweet flowers together, neither de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerves nor deſires thanks, for they intended it to none but to themſelves, and ſome private friends, whoſe importunity wrung ſome co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pies from them, and now without their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent have publiſhed it. And now ſince it is publiſhed and cannot bee ſtopped, the Lord cauſe it to worke in all his, according to that which he hath given the promiſes for to work in the hearts of his people, even to make them partakers of the divine nature. <hi>2. Pet. 1.4.</hi> And as a meanes to make them to take every day a litle poſy from the reſt, one of the promiſes gathered together, and apply it to thy ſelfe, ſee how thou ſtandeſt in need of it, and every word in it, and then apply it to thy
<pb facs="tcp:22966:118"/>ſelfe by faith, and let it ſtirre thee up to goe to God in prayer for the accompliſhment of them unto thee, then waite in the diligent uſe of all meanes for the gayning of them, and you ſhall find God not only making you heires of promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, but you ſhall be comfortable poſſeſſours of thoſe many good things which God hath pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed to Beleevers. The more you meditate, and the oftner you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ay upon them, the more good will you ſee in them, and find flow from them. I ſay no more, but I doubt not, but your experiences of good by theſe promiſes will be more then I can make knowne unto you. I de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire the God of mercies, our loving father, in our Lord Ieſus Chriſt, in whom all the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes are Yea and Amen, to make you dayly find experimentally, the truth of all his gracious promiſes.</p>
               </div>
            </body>
            <back>
               <div type="table_of_contents">
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:118"/>
                  <head>FIVE TABLES FOR THE Right and Ready finding out of any Promiſe in this Booke, for the comfortable ſupply of preſent neceſſity: the number ſhewes the page, where the Promiſe (wee would have) is to be found.</head>
                  <list>
                     <head>The <hi>1.</hi> Table, Concerning ſin.</head>
                     <item>RVles for reading the Promiſes.</item>
                     <item>If we find nothing in our ſelves that may move God. pag. 1.</item>
                     <item>If wee feare God will remember our ſinnes to puniſh them. pag. 4.</item>
                     <item>If often ſinning cauſe thee doubt of par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don. pag. 5.</item>
                     <item>If thou deſpaire. pag. 6.</item>
                     <item>If thou findeſt ſinne an heavy burden and
<pb facs="tcp:22966:119"/>Satan purſuing. pag. 8.</item>
                     <item>If thou turn from ſinne, and yet doubt of pardon. pag. 10.</item>
                     <item>If thou wouldſt have thy manifold rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lions ſubdued. pag. 13.</item>
                     <item>If thy heart be hard and full of corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. pag. 14.</item>
                     <item>If unbridled nature break out into paſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. pag. 16.</item>
                     <item>If thou be in bondage to ſome ſin. pag. 17.</item>
                     <item>If thou feareſt the breaking out of ſtrong ſinnes. pag. 18.</item>
                     <item>When thou art ſtayed from ſinne by ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition. pag. 20.</item>
                     <item>If thou feareſt God will deſtroy thee for ſinne. pag. 21.</item>
                     <item>If thou bee tempted to uncleanneſſe. pag. 22.</item>
                     <item>If thou canſt not find out thy ſinne, for which God corrects thee. pag. 23.</item>
                     <item>If thou doubt of ſalvation. pag. 24.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:119"/>
                     <head>The <hi>2.</hi> Table. Concerning Grace.</head>
                     <item>IF thine heart be as a wilderneſſe, barren of good. pag. 25.</item>
                     <item>If thou wanteſt holineſſe. pag. 29.</item>
                     <item>When thou canſt not offer up any ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice. pag. 30.</item>
                     <item>When thou feeleſt but little grace. pag. 31.</item>
                     <item>When all thy graces are weake. pag. 32.</item>
                     <item>When thy heart is dry for want of grace. pag. 35.</item>
                     <item>If thou wanteſt the ſpirit. pag. 38.</item>
                     <item>If looking on Gods love, thou canſt not love God againe. pag. 39.</item>
                     <item>If thou canſt not bring thine heart to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light in the Lord. pag. 40.</item>
                     <item>If thou feeleſt not Gods feare in thine heart. pag. 41.</item>
                     <item>If thine heart will not praiſe the Lord. page. 42.</item>
                     <item>If thou wanteſt wiſdome. pag. 43.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:120"/>
                     <item>If thou canſt not underſtand Gods voyce. pag. 44</item>
                     <item>If thou canſt not ſee into the myſteries of the Goſpell. pag. 45.</item>
                     <item>If thou ſeeſt a good way and haſt no power to walke in it. pag. 46.</item>
                     <item>If thou wanteſt memory. pag. 48.</item>
                     <item>When thou ſeeſt thine ignorance. pag. 49.</item>
                     <item>If thou deſireſt grace and art not fatisfied. pag. 52.</item>
                     <item>If thine heart be dead. pag. 54.</item>
                     <item>If thou feareſt falling away. pag. 55.</item>
                     <item>If thou art falne pag. 58.</item>
                     <item>When the Lord hath forſaken thee p. 60.</item>
                     <item>When thou feeleſt thy vileneſſe. pag. 62.</item>
                     <item>When thou feeleſt thy ſpirituall pover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. pag. 64.</item>
                     <item>When thou art in a ſtrait. pag. 65.</item>
                     <item>If thou feareſt Satan will cauſe thee to fall. pag. 67.</item>
                     <item>If thou canſt not profit by the word of God. pag. 69.</item>
                     <item>If thou findeſt thy ſelfe unlike Gods people. pag. 70.</item>
                     <item>If thou wouldſt have Gods bleſſing reſt upon thee. pag. 71.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:120"/>
                     <item>If thou wouldſt bee a bleſſing in thy place. pag. 72.</item>
                     <item>If thou ſeparateſt from the wicked in their corrupt worſhip. pag. ibid.</item>
                     <item>A promiſe to be applyed in every ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance. pag. 74.</item>
                     <item>When thou prayeſt. pag. 75.</item>
                     <item>When thou meditateſt. pag. 76.</item>
                     <item>In meditating, conferring, reading Gods word. pag. 78.</item>
                     <item>In reading of the word if thou under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandeſt not. pag. 79.</item>
                     <item>If thou canſt not conferre. pag. 80.</item>
                     <item>When thou art to goe to the aſſemblies. pag. 82.</item>
                     <item>Wouldſt thou enjoy the ordinances of God, and a bleſſing upon them. pag. 87.</item>
                     <item>If thou enjoieſt grace or meanes of grace. pag. 89.</item>
                     <item>When thou art baniſhed from Gods or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinances. pag. 91.</item>
                     <item>Whilſt thou art baniſht from Gods houſe. pag. 94.</item>
                     <item>When wicked ſheepheards are over us. pag 96.</item>
                     <item>When through wicked ſheepheards thou
<pb facs="tcp:22966:121"/>art come to great miſery. pag. 98.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The <hi>3.</hi> Table. For comfort in time of perſecution.</head>
                     <item>VVHen thou ſetteſt thy ſelfe to faſt. pag. 100.</item>
                     <item>If thou art railed upon for well doing. pag. 101.</item>
                     <item>If thou art perſeucted. pag. 102.</item>
                     <item>In partaking with Gods people in ſuffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring. pag. 104.</item>
                     <item>When thou art called to defend the truth. pag. ibid.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <head>The <hi>4.</hi> Table. Concerning earthly things.</head>
                     <item>IF thou wouldſt bring forth ſeaſonable fruit for every eſtate. pag. 106.</item>
                     <item>If thou haſt children. pag. 107.</item>
                     <item>If thou wanteſt children. pag. 109.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:121"/>
                     <item>If the Lord deny thee children. pag. 110.</item>
                     <item>If thou wouldſt have a comfortable and holy uſe of thy habitation. pag. 111.</item>
                     <item>If thou wouldſt have thy going out, and comming in bleſſed. pag. 112.</item>
                     <item>When thou eateſt or enjoyeſt any bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, that it may ſatisfy, and bee ſanctified. pag. 113.</item>
                     <item>When thou takeſt thy reſt at night, &amp;c. pag. 114.</item>
                     <item>When thou putteſt thy hand to any work. pag. 115.</item>
                     <item>If thou wouldſt have thine outward bleſſings bleſſed. pag. 116.</item>
                     <item>If thou deſireſt to enjoy the Iabours of thine hands. pag. 118.</item>
                     <item>If thou art diligent in thy calling. p. 119.</item>
                     <item>When thou ſeeſt wicked men follow unſatisfying things with reſtleſſe deſires and thou deſireſt content. pag. 120.</item>
                     <item>If thou feareſt thou ſhalt looſe by follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Lord. pag. 121.</item>
                     <item>When thou haſt loſt bleſſings by ſinne. pag. 122.</item>
                     <item>If thou feareſt loſſe of thy good name. pag. 123.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:122"/>
                     <item>If the world deſpiſe thee, &amp;c. pag. 124.</item>
                     <item>When thou art in want for ſoule or bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy. pag. 126.</item>
                     <item>In liberall giving. pag. 127.</item>
                     <item>If ſickneſſe be among us. pag. 129.</item>
                     <item>If thou feareſt death. pag. 131.</item>
                     <item>If thou feareſt untimely death. pag. 132.</item>
                     <item>If thou feareſt hurt by any of the crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. pag. 133.</item>
                     <item>When thou haſt a troubled heart. p. 134.</item>
                     <item>If thou wouldſt have thy purpoſe to proſper. pag. 135.</item>
                     <item>When thou art called to a great worke. pag. 136.</item>
                     <item>In times of danger. pag. 138.</item>
                     <item>When thou art in great troubles. &amp;c. pag. 139.</item>
                     <item>When thou ſeemeſt to bee forgotten in affliction. pag. 141.</item>
                     <item>When thou feareſt to dye in miſery. pag. 142.</item>
                     <item>When thy ſorrowes grow great. p. 143.</item>
                     <item>When thou knoweſt no way out of miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry for ſoule or body. pag. 145.</item>
                     <item>If thou wouldſt have deliverance out of trouble. pag. 146.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:122"/>
                     <item>If thine enemies prevaile. pag. 147.</item>
                     <item>That thou maiſt be delivered, and thine enemies afflicted. pag. 149.</item>
                     <item>If thou wouldſt have thine enemies de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, &amp;c. pag. 150.</item>
                     <item>If the wicked plot againſt thee. p. 151.</item>
                     <item>In the troubles of the Church. pag. 152.</item>
                     <item>For the fall of Antichriſt. pag. 153.</item>
                     <item>For the calling of the Iewes. pag. 154.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:123"/>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:123"/>
                     <head>The <hi>5.</hi> Table. For the Saints ſupport in time of trouble.</head>
                     <item>THat God hath freely loved his Elect in Chriſt Ieſus. pag. 1.</item>
                     <item>That God hath given Chriſt to death for his Elect. pag. 2.</item>
                     <item>That we are are freely juſtified by Ieſus Chriſt. pag. 3.</item>
                     <item>That God hath made a covenant with his Children to be their God. pag. 4.</item>
                     <item>That God will call his children to the knowledge of his truth. pag. 5.</item>
                     <item>That God will give his Spirit unto his Childern. pag. 6.</item>
                     <item>That God will cauſe his children to truſt in him by faith. pag. 7.</item>
                     <item>That God will give his children an humble and broken heart. pag. 8.</item>
                     <item>That Gods children ſhall have power to mortify and over come ſinne. pag. 9.</item>
                     <item>That the children of God ſhall live a ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and ſanctified life. pag. ib.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:124"/>
                     <item>That they ſhall love God. pag. 10.</item>
                     <item>That God will give his children hearts to delight in all his holy Ordinances. p. 11.</item>
                     <item>That God will give his Children hearts to feare and ſerve him. pag. 12.</item>
                     <item>That God will give his Children hearts to ſeeke him by prayer. pag. 13.</item>
                     <item>That God will heare the prayers of his Children. pag. 14.</item>
                     <item>That wee may perſevere in grace. pag. 15.</item>
                     <item>That God will give vnto his Children the good things of this life. pag. 16.</item>
                     <item>That God will guide his Children by his ſpeciall providence in all their wayes. pag. 17.</item>
                     <item>That God will bleſſe thoſe which are diligent in their Calling. pag. 18.</item>
                     <item>That God will bleſſe thoſe that keep his Sabbaths. pag. ibid,</item>
                     <item>That God will reward thoſe that are fruitfull in good works. pag. 19.</item>
                     <item>That we ſhall receive good by the ſoci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ety of the faithfull. pag. 21.</item>
                     <item>That God will keep afflictions from his children as it may be for their good. p. 22.</item>
                     <pb facs="tcp:22966:124"/>
                     <item>That other wiſe God will be with, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve, and keep his children in afflictions that they hurt them not. pag. 23.</item>
                     <item>That God will deliver his childen out off afflictions in his due time. pag. 24.</item>
                     <item>That God will ſanctify all afflictions for the good of his children. pag. 25.</item>
                     <item>That God in his owne time will ſubdue all the enemies of his Church. pag. 26.</item>
                     <item>That the children of God ſhall dye hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily. pag. 28.</item>
                     <item>That the juſt ſhall be raiſed unto eter. nall life. pag. ib.</item>
                     <item>That God will reward the labours of the righteous in the life to come. pag. 29.</item>
                     <item>That God will make good and perform all that he hath promiſed. pag. 30.</item>
                  </list>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:125"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:22966:125"/>
               </div>
            </back>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
